<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 9. of Iune. 1605 Vpon the 20. of the Reuelation the 12. vers. treating of these seuerall heads. 1. Of the resurrection of the flesh. 2. Of the iudgement of the quicke and dead. 3. Of the communion of saints, 4. Of euerlasting life. By Samuell Gardnier [sic], Doct. of Diuinitie.</title>
            <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1605</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 100 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 34 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A01455</idno>
            <idno type="STC">STC 11581</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC S118176</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99853385</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99853385</idno>
            <idno type="VID">18768</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A01455)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 18768)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1475-1640 ; 1236:18)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Paules Crosse the 9. of Iune. 1605 Vpon the 20. of the Reuelation the 12. vers. treating of these seuerall heads. 1. Of the resurrection of the flesh. 2. Of the iudgement of the quicke and dead. 3. Of the communion of saints, 4. Of euerlasting life. By Samuell Gardnier [sic], Doct. of Diuinitie.</title>
                  <author>Gardiner, Samuel, b. 1563 or 4.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[68] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed [by E. Allde] for Edward VVhite, and are to be solde at the little North-doore of Saint Paules Church, at the signe of the Gun,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1605.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Printer's name from STC.</note>
                  <note>Signatures: A-H⁴ I² .</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Jesus College (University of Cambridge). Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-11</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON PREACHED <hi>at Paules Croſſe the</hi> 9. <hi>of</hi> Iune. 1605.</p>
            <p>
               <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>pon the 20. of the Reuelation the 12. verſ. treating of theſe <hi>ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerall heads.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. <hi>Of the Reſurrection of the Fleſh.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>2. <hi>Of the Iudgement of the quicke and dead.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>3. <hi>Of the Communion of Saints.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>4. <hi>Of Euerlaſting life.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
            <p>By <hi>Samuell Gardnier,</hi> Doct. of Diuinitie.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON</hi> Printed for <hi>Edward VVhite,</hi> and are to be ſolde at the little North-doore of Saint Paules Church, at <hi>the Signe of the Gun.</hi> 1605.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:2"/>
            <head>TO <hi>THE RIGHT HONO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable</hi> and vertuous Lady, <hi>Jane</hi> Lady <hi>Barkley,</hi> wife to Henry Lord Barkley.</head>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">I</seg>N the full affiance</hi> I haue in the Lordes mercie, which made this poore Sermon, welcome to ſo many eares, being preached: that hee will direct it to the com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon comfort, being now preſented to their eyes printed: the importu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie of many of my good friends had ſucceſſe with me.</p>
            <p>I conſecrate it, moſt Honorable Lady, vnto you, in token of duetie towards you: for your great Loue, by which I am enabled to labour in this ſort, and indeede to liue. Gods bleſſing be vpon it, and vpon you.</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>Your Honors Chaplaine, SAMVEL GARDNIER.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:3"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:3"/>
            <epigraph>
               <bibl>Reuelat. 20. Verſ. 12</bibl>
               <q>¶ And J ſawe the dead both great and <hi>ſmall ſtand before God, and the Bookes were</hi> opened, and an other Booke was opened, which is the Booke of Life, and the dead were iudged of thoſe thinges, which were written in the Bookes according to their workes.</q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>
               <hi>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">H</seg>Eere is cluſter, and</hi> multiplicitie of Chriſtian Catechiſme, as including and concluding theſe foure Articles of the ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholique faith. 1. <hi>The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection of the flesh,</hi> touched in the ſtanding of the dead before God. 2. <hi>The iudgement of the quicke and the dead,</hi> noted in the opening of the Bookes, out of which they haue the ſentence of iudgement reade them. 3. <hi>The Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints.</hi> 4. <hi>Euerlaſting life,</hi> not obſcurely inſinuated by the other booke, entitled: <hi>The Booke of life,</hi> heere ſpoken of.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:4"/>
            <p>This ſentence is an abſolute deſcriptio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, wherin we haue theſe circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ces. 1. The per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons ſtanding in the iudgement to bee tryed. <hi>All.</hi> 1 <hi>Greate,</hi> 2. <hi>Small,</hi> of what note &amp; marke ſoeuer they be 2. The manner of trial &amp; proceeding with them, by the billes of enditement found out againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in the opening the bookes. 3. The doome definitiue of dou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble nature. 1. Abſolution. 2. Condemnation accor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding to the propertie and condition of their workes.</p>
            <p>The precedencie is an introduction to this, which telleth vs the perſon of the iudge in the immediate verſe before, which is Chriſt the Sonne of God, the Sonne of man,<note place="margin">John. 5.22.</note> 
               <hi>to whome all the iudgement is commit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by the father, being the predestinate man, by whome he will iudge the world in righteouſnes,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.31.</note> whoſe maieſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ie is there depicted vnto vs, in his orient colours, an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwerable in effect to that which <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: <hi>vide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitur terribilis, qui viſus eſt contemptibilis, demonſtra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bit potentiam, qui demonſtrauit patientiam.</hi> He ſhall be ſeene terrible, that hath bene ſeene contemptible, and he ſhall manifeſt his power, as hee hath ſhewed his patience. And thus I pretermit the purport of the premiſes with this ſentence of monition giuen you out of <hi>Augustin:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. in Pſal. 66.</note> 
               <hi>Deut ſe corrigendos, dent ſe dirigen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dos, ei qui videt iudicandos.</hi> Let them yeeld to be cor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected, let them yeeld to be directed, to him that one day ſhall ſee them all detected.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:4"/>
            <p> That which is firſt in nature, is heere handled firſt in order: the learning of the reſurrectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, the fore run<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner of the iudgement &amp; the conſequents thereof: taught in the verie entrie in theſe wordes. <hi>I ſawe the dead both great and ſmall stand before God.</hi> The re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection is the hand that holdeth vp religio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> by the head: the life and ſoule of it, the firſt ſtone that we are to lay in our ſpiritual building, or rather the founda<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion that beareth vp the building, the anker of our hope, the certaintie of our ſaluation, called by <hi>Ter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tullian, Ianua regni caelestis.</hi> The doore whereat wee enter into the Kingdome of heauen, the Godly ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by going to the ioyes, the wicked to the torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared for them: the refere<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce of our faith by the ſame Godly Father, <hi>Fiducia Chriſtianorum est reſurrectio mortuorum:</hi> Our Chriſtian expectation is the corpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rall reſurrection, which is grounded on the Doctrine of Saint <hi>Paul,</hi> who bringeth in bundles of reaſons for it by order of iuſt conſequence thus: If there were no reſurrection. 1. <hi>Then were our preaching vaine.</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> 1.</note> 2. <hi>Your faith of none effect.</hi> 3. <hi>VVee should be found falſe wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſes.</hi> 4. <hi>The dead were quite vndone.</hi> 5. <hi>VVe were yet in our ſinnes.</hi> 6. <hi>Of all men, Christians were most mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerable.</hi> As if he ſhold haue ſaid, take away the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and take away altogeather, our preaching, your beleeuing, burne the Bible, throw downe pul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pits, lay our churches euen with their foundations,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:5"/>play the Epicures &amp; belli-gods, and liue as ye liſt. For the Bookes are found lyars, the Prophets &amp; Apoſtles haue fed vs with fables, &amp; they are as Fountains dry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vp. But our foundations are in the holy hilles, and not in the valleies of humane reaſons, we know what wee beleeue, and wee lay ſtedfaſt holde of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection &amp; of faith towards Chriſt.<note place="margin">Pſal. 3.21.</note> 
               <hi>VVho shall change our vile body that it may be fashioned like his glorious body, according to the working, whereby he is able euen to ſubdue all thinges vnto himſelfe.</hi> But yet there is more oppugnation, and inſurrection, againſt this ſweete Article of the reſurrection, then againſt any parcell of Diuinitie beſide: the deuill and his blacke guard, bending and banding themſelues againſt this, withall the might and mallice that they can. 1. By <hi>Gentils.</hi> 2. By <hi>Iewes,</hi> without and within the Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties of the Church. Without, by the <hi>Peripatecians,</hi> and almoſt al the broode of Brainſicke Philoſophers and ſchoole of Epicures, among whome, heere what <hi>Seneca,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca ad Martiam.</note> one of the beſt of that bunch, ſaith: <hi>Mors omnium ſolutio eſt et finis, extra quam mala noſtra non exeant.</hi> Death is the Period and determination of al things, beyond which they cannot goe. And he ſtan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deth to reaſon it, and maintaine it in this wiſe: <hi>Quo modo poteſt miſer eſſe qui nullus eſt?</hi> How can he be a wretched man that is no man? But there are in the Church that ſpeake proudlye and peruerſly againſt
<pb facs="tcp:18768:5"/>this excellent Diuinity, eyther marring it altogether, or (which is little better) making it in their owne moulds, caſting cloudes &amp; fume vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the cleare light of the Scriptures, making a ſpiritual reſurrection co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiſting in our renua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce &amp; regeneration. Such were the Sadduces among the Iewes, put to a <hi>non plus,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 22.33</note> and ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence by our Sauiour: Such were <hi>Hymeneus</hi> and <hi>Phi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>letus,</hi> while the Apoſtles liued &amp; taught among them, taxed by ſaint <hi>Paul</hi> in his letter to <hi>Timothee.</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 2.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> Such were the <hi>Athenians</hi> verie troubleſome to the ſame A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle, no ſooner he touched this text of the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, how be it they heard him willingly the forepart of the Sermon:<note place="margin">Act. 17.32</note> and ſuth are the mockers &amp; ſcoffers of whom ſaint <hi>Peter</hi> ſpeaketh that this laſt age ſhuld bring foorth,<note place="margin">2. Pet. 3.4</note> who ſhall haue in deriſion whatſoeuer Preachers out of Scriptures ſhall tell them of the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, the iudgement &amp; the worlds deſtruction, Such was <hi>Simon Magus,</hi> from whome came the ſect of the <hi>Simonians.</hi> Such were the <hi>Valentinians, Carpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cratians, Cardonians, Archotici, Seuerians, Baſilidi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans, Hierarchites,</hi> with rablements of ſuch Locuſts &amp; Caterpillars, of whome <hi>Augustine</hi> hath entreated. Such were the <hi>Manichees</hi> that were mainely bent a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt this Article, againſt whom ſaint <hi>Augustin</hi> wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thyly diſputeth: ſuch a one was <hi>Martion,</hi> who was no faithfull friend to the reſurrection, as <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his fift Booke witneſſeth. But that euerie mouth may
<pb facs="tcp:18768:6"/>be ſtopped, God gloryfied, our faith ſtrengthned, we ſhall. 1. by authorities of Scriptures. 2. Sacred ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amples. 3. Reaſons irrefragable. 4. The whole courſe of nature make good this propoſition, and winde it vp with the vſe, and applycation that it giueth, and paſſe on to the reſt.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In both the inſtruments the olde and the new, wee are compaſſed with cloudes of witneſſes in the cauſe.<note place="margin">Iſaiah. 26.19</note> The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> thus ſpeaketh in it. <hi>Thy dead men shal liue: euen with my body shall they riſe. Awake and ſing ye that dwell in duſt: for thy dew is as the dew of hearbes, and the earth shal caſt out the dead.</hi> Liuely illuſtration heerof is in the dead bones,<note place="margin">Ezech. 37.10</note> which by <hi>Ezechiel</hi> his prophecying vpon them, recouered their ioyntes,<note place="margin">Dan. 12.2</note> ſinnewes, fleſh, skinne, life. <hi>Daniel</hi> mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth this as cleere as the Sunne, when as hee ſaith: <hi>Many of them that ſleepe in the duſt of the earth shall awake, ſome to euerlaſting life, and ſome to shame and perpetuall contempt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 17.16</note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> is as plaine and open in the point. <hi>As for me, I will behold thy preſence in righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teouſnes: and when I wake vp after thy likeneſſe, I shal be ſatisfied with it.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Job. 19.25</note> But <hi>Iob</hi> ſtriketh the naile to the head, who amidſt all his perturbations and paſsions, maketh this profeſsion. <hi>I am ſure that my redeemer liueth, and hee shall stand the last on the earth. And though after my skinne wormes deſtroy this bodye, yet shall I ſee God in my flesh, whome I my ſelfe shal
<pb facs="tcp:18768:6"/>ſee, and mine eyes shall beholde, and noue other for mee, though my reines are conſumed within mee.</hi> There be more places in the olde Teſtament beſides theſe: but theſe are bones enough to choake them that are ſo impudent as to ſay, that the olde Charter performeth no teſtimonie to this preſent article: or if there bee any one to be found, that it was vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowne to the Fathers of thoſe times. I am driuen to deale with the proofes of the new Teſtament, as <hi>Salomon</hi> did with the braſſe in the Temple: it was ſo much he would not weigh it: they are ſo many, we cannot ſtand vpon them.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Examples of ſuch as haue been raiſed from the dead, doe nouriſh and fortifie our faith in the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection,<note place="margin">1. Ki. 17.22 2. Kin. 4.35 Math. 9.25 Luke. 7.15 Ioh. 11.44 Act. 9.40 Act. 20.10</note> as of the widdowes Sonne of <hi>Zarephath</hi> raiſed by <hi>Elijah:</hi> of the <hi>Shunamites</hi> Sonne reſtored by <hi>Elisha,</hi> of <hi>Iairus</hi> his Daughter, the <hi>widdowes</hi> Sonne of the Citie of <hi>Naijm, Lazarus</hi> that had lyen in his graue foure dayes, brought from death to life againe by Chriſt, <hi>Tabytha</hi> by <hi>Peter: Eutichus</hi> by <hi>Paul.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. There are fundamentall reaſons on the ſide of the reſurrection that ought to ſway with vs. 1. We draw the firſt from the Iuſtice of God, which would that the bodie which hath partaked with the minde, in the good or badde inclinations thereof, ſhould bee rewarded accordinglye: which not being ſo
<pb facs="tcp:18768:7"/>perfourmed in this life, it could neuer be ſerued in nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber, meaſure, proportio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, without the reſurrection. 2. We alſo diſpute from his infinite goodnes, which plenteouſly rewardeth the well dooer: and his anger implacable, (worſer, as <hi>Chriſoſtome</hi> faith, then a thou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſand helles) which muſt make an end, or rather no end with the workers of wickednes: both which were quite voided, were there a nullity of the reſurrection. 3. We further argue from the immutabilitie of his veritie, his promiſes being ſigned by the finger of his ſpirit, and ſealed with the blood of the Lambe, of ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nor, glorie, peace, a crowne of immortalitie, the frui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the tree of life, the ſight of the glorious face of God, the ſocietie with his Angels and Saints, the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation of firſt borne, new names, white garments, pleaſures at the right hand of God, abundance of ioyes for euermore: all which muſt take place by the reſurrection. 4. Finally, our dignitie and excellencie aboue all other creatures, (wherein we goe as much beyond them, as the Moone doth the ſmaller Stars in glory) challengeth the ſame: which without the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition of the life to come, ſhould be many wayes in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feriour vnto them. For as the earth with the other e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lements are of longer ſtanding then man: ſo there be among Birdes, Beaſtes, Fiſhes, that are of greater ſtrength and longer life then he. And whereas almoſt all creatures immediately after they bee producted
<pb facs="tcp:18768:7"/>can ſhift for themſelues, and haue eyther no, or little neede others: man-kinde onely muſt haue need of great atte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dance, &amp; aſsiſtance, his time is ſhorter then of many of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, &amp; his miſeries more then any of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore there muſt be an other life to reco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pence it.</p>
            <p n="4">4. But becauſe it pleaſeth the Philoſophers to ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raigne the Scriptures of follie, and meaſure Diuinitie by the line of humane wiſedome, and cannot main<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tain this <hi>maxime</hi> of their ſchoole <hi>a priuatione ad ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bitum impoſsibilis regreſſus,</hi> from the priuation to the habit, the returne is impoſsible, vnles they flatly diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime the reſurrection: and the Atheiſt rubbeth his filthines againſt Gods holynes, and ſcorneth whatſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer is ſpoken out of ſcriptures, (whereby our fore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cited teſtimonies, examples, reaſons, grounded vpon them, concerne not their profeſsio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>) we wil deale with them, by their owne learning, the order of nature, which is euerie ones Schoolemaiſter, and that ſhall ſtint the ſtrife that is between vs, &amp; make the queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on queſtionles.</p>
            <p>There be many good reſemblances in the workes of nature, of the reſurection in creatures of al kindes. 1. Vegetatiue. 2. Senſitiue. 3. Rationall, which albe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>it they bee not proofes ſo pregnant: yet giue they good enforcement to the preſent argument.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Out of things vegetatiue, that haue but a grow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing life: groweth verie good probabilitie of this ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred
<pb facs="tcp:18768:8"/>miſterie.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 15, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>6</note> As of Corne, (which is <hi>Pauls</hi> compari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, and brought in by him to prooue the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on) which firſt rotteth, and dyeth in the ground, and againe in the ſpring, the renewing time of the ſeaſon, reuiueth and flouriſheth, yea the earth with all her ſtirpes, hearbs, plants, yeild to the wrath &amp; wracke of the winter, and decay, &amp; die away: and draw their breath againe at the returne of the times, and put on their new habit and attire with which they ſtatelie mantle and adorne the ſurface of the earth, and plen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tifullie ſerue for the vſe of man.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To come to thinges ſenſitiue: there be among them ſenſible and ſignificant ſignes of the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, <hi>Hiſtorians</hi> of verie good worth make report, that there bee certaine <hi>Beares</hi> and <hi>Mice,</hi> who ſleepe whole winters without repaſt, and that in ſuch ſort, as by no agitation, and compunction that is vſed, they can be perceiued to ſtirre, vntill the ſpring of the yeare, when they awake againe, and ſhew themſelues abroad out of their Caues and Dennes. The Indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>an Bird the <hi>Phoenix</hi> (as witneſſeth <hi>Lactantius</hi>) is burnt to aſhes by the power of the Sunne, and out of the ſame aſhes another is quickned, wherby that kind is preſerued. The Lyon miſsing of her pray, is longer from her whelpes, who returning finding them dead, roareth ſo outragiouſly as ſhe recoue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reth them.</p>
            <p n="3">
               <pb facs="tcp:18768:8"/> 3. But in the reaſonable and royall creature, which is man, this matter is manifeſted, he is conceiued an infant in his mothers wombe, where of liquid ſeede thinges of ſundry natures are producted, as fleſh, bones, ſinewes, veines, haire: in the wombe he is qua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lified with vitall Spirits, where he liueth, moo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth, feedeth, at the laſt out of the wombe, as out of a winding ſheete, hee commeth into the world. Who is ſo ſtockiſh as cannot heere perceiue, ſpecial good token, &amp; tipe of the reſurrection? To preſſe this point further, that man may bee inſtance of mans re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection, dooth not euerie man euerie day as it were dye by his ſleepe, which is the ligature of his ſences and reaſon, there being ſuch cognati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on betweene death and ſleepe, as ſleepe is termed by Philoſophers, <hi>Imago mortis,</hi> the Image of death, and by <hi>Homer, Frater mortis,</hi> the Brother of death.</p>
            <p>For what office doth hee performe of a liuing man, while hee lyeth like a tymber logge in his dead ſleepe. But his ſleepe being diſpelled, hee is a new man, and returneth a freſh to his wonted labours, Doe wee not alſo ſee how many are caſt into ſownes and traunces, which for a time ſeeme to depriue them of breath and life: and yet doe recouer themſelues againe. Theſe bee to mee ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry good memorialls of my good reſurrection,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:9"/>and they preach the like to you. Finally, the verie diſtinction of the times, readeth this Diuinity lecture vnto vs, while the day is buried in the darkenes of the night, as it were in a Sepulcher, &amp; ſo rowleth a ſtone ouer it, as it cannot, vntill the dawning, breake out a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine. The like we ſay of the night which dyeth by the day. The ſeaſons die and depart from vs, and liue and returne againe: all thinges by deformitie are re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed. Theſe be <hi>Tertullians</hi> arguments in <hi>Apolo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>getico</hi> to prooue the reſurrection againſt the Ge<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tils. But to the aduerſaries of this Doctrine, it ſeemeth a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt reaſon, and to bee impoſsible, that of nothing any thing ſhould be made, &amp; ſo that a body, by death as they ſay, reſolued into nothing, ſhould become a bodie againe, we anſwere them heerein, that it is <hi>ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prarationem, non contra rationem:</hi> aboue reaſon, but not againſt reaſon it ſhould be ſo. And <hi>Potentia fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cientis eſt ratio facti.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Aug. Epiſt. <hi>3.</hi> ad volus.</note> 
               <hi>Conſidera authorem, tolle dubita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tionem,</hi> it is <hi>Augustines</hi> ſaying: The power of the do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is the reaſon of the deede. Conſider the Author &amp; doe away all doubt, the reaſon of the reſurrection of the creature, is the power of the creator, there being nothing of impoſsible condition with God, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plieth not a contradictio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as the ſchoole-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> doe diſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>inguiſh. And it is falſe they ſay: that the bodie by death is diſſolued to nothing, for it is but turned into his element, the earth, the Rocke from which it was
<pb facs="tcp:18768:9"/>firſt hewed, the pitte from whence it was firſt digged and to take vp the forme of the ſpeech of the Philo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſopher, in <hi>materiam priman,</hi> into his firſt matter, of which it was firſt made, into which it ſhal be marred, &amp; out of which it ſhal be made againe. Why ſhould it ſeeme to you harder for God, to reſtore that which once was, then to create at the firſt of nothing that which neuer was? Are Artificers and workemen in Metalles able to diſſolue ſuch veſſels as they liſt, &amp; to make them new againe? Can Glaſiers doe the like in that brittle ware? to let paſſe Potters, and Plodders in clay, who can marre and make any vtenſill of that fragile nature, as many times as they pleaſe. And ſhall not the great maiſter work-man of the whole world be able to doe the like? Spend &amp; diſperſe my bodie, ſo farre as force of imagination wil ſuffer you, ſuppoſe a Beaſt eateth it, an other beaſt prayeth vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon him, and that beaſt againe is deuoured by birds, thoſe Birds are incorporated by men, and ſo my ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance is after many concoctions and degrees, tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fuſed into many mens ſubſtance: the Lord ſhal ſun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der and deuide them againe, aſwel as the Crafteſ-me<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> can part ſundrie metals that are moulten together.</p>
            <p>But we are not to conceiue, that euerie thing that giueth increaſe to the bodies ſubſtance, is to riſe a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gaine in the reſurrection: but that euerie one ſhall haue ſuch ſufficiencie of dimenſions, as ſhal ſerue for
<pb facs="tcp:18768:10"/>a perfect and abſolute bodie. But be it that the bodie is to take vp that ſtature in the reſurrection, which is laide downe by diſſolution (as ſome ſtiflie de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend it, whome wee will not offend in it, with the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrictions and cautions that <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſpeaketh of, that we free it of <hi>deformitie,</hi>
               <note place="margin">De Ciuit. lei lib, <hi>22,</hi> cap, <hi>20.</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>infirmitie, tarditie, im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puritie</hi>) and be it neuer ſo piece-meale diuided ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the former ſuppoſition, the like whereof <hi>Auguſtine</hi> maketh in the ſame place, euerie part muſt againe bee reſtored to the right owner, as being but borrowed for the time, as the ſame father ſaith.</p>
            <p>But wee conclude this, with theſe graue and re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerend words of this man: <hi>Abſit vt ſinus vllus, ſecre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tumque naturae,</hi>
               <note place="margin">ibidem.</note> 
               <hi>ita recipiat aliquid ſubtractum ſenſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus nostris, vt omnium creatoris aut lateat cognitio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nem, aut effugiat poteſtatem.</hi> Bee it farre from vs to thinke that any ſecret place, or conueyance of nature, ſhould ſo hide any thing remooued from our ſences, as it may be kept from the knowledge of the Creator, or eſcape his power.</p>
            <p>It remaineth that wee reape the Harueſt of this Doctrine, and the Vintage this Diuinitie giueth vs: much being to be gathered and gleaned from hence.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The reſurrection is a comfort to the Godlye, and a corſiue to the wicked. So our Sauiour Chriſt
<pb facs="tcp:18768:10"/>ſaith of it:<note place="margin">Ioh. 5.29.</note> 
               <hi>They shall come foorth that haue done good to the reſurrection of life: but they that haue done euill to the reſurrection of condemnation.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Heare the Godlye ſowe in teares, they ſhall then reape in ioy: heere they labour and are heauie loden, there they ſhall reſt from their labours, and take out their generall <hi>quietus eſt.</hi> And that is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>koning <hi>Dauid</hi> maketh of it ſaying:<note place="margin">Pſal. 16.9.</note> 
               <hi>Mine heart is glad, my tongue reioyceth, and my flesh alſo doth rest in hope,</hi> the effect of the reſurrection as the addition ſheweth: <hi>For thou shalt not leaue my ſoule in graue, neither wilt thou ſuffer thine holy one to ſee corrupti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi> Wherefore the reſurrection is ſtiled by <hi>Peter,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 3.19 Ma. 5.4.6 Reu. 17.1 Reuel. 21</note> 
               <hi>the time of refreshing:</hi> for the hungrie ſhall bee ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſfyed, which is their refreſhing: the mour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners comforted, which is their refreſhing: all teares wiped away from our eyes, which is our refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing: death ſhall bee no more, nor ſorrowe, nor crying, nor any more paine, which is our grati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous generall refreſhing.</p>
            <p>The reſurrection as <hi>Augustine</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">
                  <hi>August</hi> Pſal. 10.</note> 
               <hi>Eſt for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>midenda malis propter paenam: amanda bonis prop<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter coronam.</hi> It is fearefull to the wicked for the ſtroke of Iuſtice: it is welcome to the Godlye for the crowne of righteouſnes. As two that are caſt into the Gaole, the one for a Capital, the other for a common offence, entertaine the time of the
<pb facs="tcp:18768:11"/>aſsiſes and comming of the Iudge, with contrarie af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fection, as being this mans abſolution, &amp; the other mans condemnation, and therefore the one is incou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raged, and the other is caſt downe, when this time commeth: ſo the good in the reſurection holde vp their heads, for their gaole deliuerie and redemption is at hand, the bad hang downe their heads, and are out of ſoule, for their ſwift damnation commeth. This calleth vpon vs for our ſpeedie repentance, leaſt that day as a ſnare vnawares come vpon vs: For ſuch as this time leaue vs, ſuch ſhall that time finde vs: <hi>Qualis quiſque in isto die moritur,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iug. heſych piſt, <hi>8</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>talis in die illo iu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicabitur:</hi> as a man dyeth in this day, ſo ſhall he bee iudged in that day.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The certaine expectation of the reſurrection, and the due and duetiful meditation of it, ſerueth to rouſe vs vp from our beddes of ſecurity, to take vs by the elbowes and ſet vs on our feete, and much fruite groweth vpon the ſtalke. It powreth water vpon the Furnace of our furious affections and cooleth them, it is the watch and the dyall by which we are direct<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed to ſpend our time, and it is the fanne that fifteth and winnoweth the pelfe from the corne, the ſtaffe of our iourney towards heauen more fortunate then <hi>Iacobs</hi> was, with which he paſſed ouer <hi>Iordan,</hi> the ſtarre that leadeth the Godly wiſe to the heauen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly <hi>Bethlehem,</hi> where Chriſt is, as the Commet led the
<pb facs="tcp:18768:11"/>wiſemen of the eaſt to <hi>Bethlehem</hi> where Chriſt was.</p>
            <p>He that hath a yerely great inheritance may ſpend ſomewhat liberally, but he that oweth more then he is worth muſt not ſpend an idle penny, as being to ſtand to the curteſie of his creditor that will call him to a reckoning. It ſo fareth with vs, we are already much caſt behinde hand, as hauing ſpent too much time already vpon our pleaſures and our ſinnes: it remaineth now that we apply our ſelues to the Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles counſell, <hi>to redeeme the time, becauſe the daies are euill,</hi> and to ioyne in petition to God with <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid; O let me liue and recouer my ſelfe, before I goe hence, and be no more ſeene.</hi> The ſerious thought of this draue <hi>Ierom</hi> to his dumpes, and pricked him in the quickeſt vaine, whatſoeuer he went about, hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the voice of the iudgement ſounding in his eares, of which he ſaith thus: <hi>ſiue vigilo ſiue dormio, ſiue aliquidaliud ago, videor mihi audire vocem hanc in aure mea, ſurgite mortui, venite ad iudicium:</hi> whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther I awake or ſleepe, or whatſoeuer elſe I doe, I ſeeme to heare this voice, ringing in mine eares. Awake ye dead and come to iudgement. The ſound of this trumpet awaketh vs all, and it is a Spur to the Godly to prick them vnto vertue, and a bridle to the wicked to holde them in fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vice. While the Apoſtle fed vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> this, as vpon a reſtoratiue. <hi>That the reſurrec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the dead should be of the iust and vniust,</hi> how
<pb facs="tcp:18768:12"/>it wrought, he telleth vs. <hi>In this reſpect I endeauour my ſelfe to haue alwaies a cleare conſcience towards God and man.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 24.15.16.</note>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. The faith in the reſurrection ſerueth to ſcatter our inordinate paſſions, which naturally ſtrangle vs for our deceaſed friends and to keepe them with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in the limits and boundes of orderly modera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</p>
            <p>While we conſider how death that ſlayeth vs all, is ſlaine in the electe by the generall reſurrection, that <hi>non obijt, ſed abijt: non amiſimus ſed premiſin us.</hi> He is not loſt,<note place="margin">Gen. 15.15 Num. 27.13</note> but left for a while, he is but gone with <hi>Abraham</hi> to his fathers, as heere liuing, but among ſtrangers: he is but gathered to his people with <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> as being heere but ſcattered: his fleſh ſlee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ping and reſting in hope with <hi>Dauids,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 16.9.</note> eaſing himſelfe after ſuch wearyſome labours of this life, which being finiſhed hee ariſeth there fully to his endleſſe felicitye, his ſoule all the while being in Gods cuſtodye, and his ſpirit in the hands of the Lord of the ſpirits of all fleſh, as <hi>Dauid</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth vs in his laſt wil and teſtament, leauing his king<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome to his Son, his carkas to the ſoyle, and to God his ſoule,<note place="margin">Pſal. 31.5.</note> ſaying: <hi>Into thy hands I commend my ſpi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, for thou hast redeemed me, O Lord thou God of truth,</hi> which the ſecond <hi>Dauid</hi> of the ſeede of <hi>Da<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uid</hi> ſampleth, committing his ſoule to no other kee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:12"/>then to the Creator as being there moſte ſure, as the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">Luk 23, 46</note> 
               <hi>I know whome I haue be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeued, and I am perſwaded,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Tim. 1, 12</note> 
               <hi>that hee is able to keepe that which I haue committed to him against that day.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="4">4. While wee aſſertaine our ſelues of the reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection, and reſt our ſelues in that as Doues in the cleftes of the rockes, we are armed and prepared a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the terror of death, for wee conſider howe God hath turned it into our benefit, and made it our entrance into a better life, our paſſage from a priſon to a pallace, from a tabernacle to an abi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding Cittie: from a region of death, to the land of the liuing: from the life of men, to the life of Angelles: from a bodie of humillitie, to a bodie of glorye: from the vale of teares, to that mount of <hi>Sion,</hi> where the Lambe is gathering the Saints about him, to the copartnerſhippe of thoſe ioyes, which hee himſelfe enioyeth according to that which the Apoſtle ſaith:<note place="margin">2, Cor, 5, 1</note> 
               <hi>VVee knowe that when our earthlie houſe of this tabernacle shall bee diſsolued: wee haue a building giuen of God, which is an houſe not made with handes, but eternall in the heauens.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>What man hath beene thrown into a deepe dun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion without light of Sun or Mooneful of Serpents, and all vile creatures, would not bee glad to bee
<pb facs="tcp:18768:13"/>ſet at libertie? our death &amp; reſurrection is this great mutation, the bodie being the priſon of the ſoule, and the graue the priſon of the bodie: the bodie be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing as ful of ſinnes as any priſon is of Serpents in this life, and heauen being the pallace of our endleſſe pleaſures. What man maketh not haſt for his life out of an olde houſe readie to fall? our bodies are no better then old clay: cottages ready to drop downe: our ſpirit is but vapour and fume, our garments are corruption, the worme and cancker, our portion, the earth, the wombe that did conceiue vs, and the earth, the wombe that muſt receiue vs. If a skilfull Pilote ſhall foreſee and foretell a ſtorme, ſhall not the Mariners haſt all that they may towards the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen? Chriſt our great Ship-maiſter hath foreſpoken many ſtormes in the ſea of this world: hie we there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to heauen, which is our hauen, to the key-ſide of the kingdome of God, &amp; to the land of the liuing, the landing place of vs all. In the ioynd Battell with the worldly enemie, when our ſouldiers are ſtrooken with gun ſhot on al ſides, and our fellowes fall before vs, and behinde vs, on the right hand, and the left, what a happie turne is it for the enemie to turne his backe to vs, and betake him to his heeles, and how would this quicken and hearten our Spirits? but by the reſurrection, all the ranckes and Claſſeis of our enemies, the deuill, death, condemnation, turne vs
<pb facs="tcp:18768:13"/>their backe partes and flie away from vs. The day labourer is glad whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the day is at an end, for the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> his reſt and his reward beginneth: the end of this life is the end of our labour, and then our reſt and reward without end beginneth.</p>
            <p>Euerie man is glad at the departure of Winter, and at the approach of Sommer: this life of ours is but a troubleſome Winter, the life that is to come is the ioyfull Sommer ſeaſon.</p>
            <p>Hee is a braineleſſe begger indeede, that would not put off his rotten ragges, to bee clad with roy<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all robes: our hides that couer vs are paltrie lea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther coates, and as filthy as any Beggers weedes: but in the other life wee ſhall bee cloathed with the white garment of Chriſtes innocency, who ſhall change the vile rayment of our bodies, and ſhall decke them with all glorie and Maieſtye ſuta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble to his bodye. The traueller that hath beene long in farre parts, is a glad man when his buſines are at an end, that he may returne to his wife, children, and friendes: our life is but a wearieſome pilgrimage, of fewe and euil daies: by death and the reſurrection wee haue a merrie meeting withall our kindred, and deare friendes departed in the Lordes feare. Hee that is out-lawed and baniſhed for debt, is made a merrie man by his calling home againe, and the cancelling that debt: wee liue heere debtors
<pb facs="tcp:18768:14"/>and baniſhed men, the Lord calleth vs home by the way of our death, and throweth all our tickets of ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>counts into the ſea. Why therfore ſhould not our hearts skip like Rammes within our bellyes for ioy? If <hi>Dauid, Paul, Peter, Iohn,</hi> or any of theſe great men and deare Saints of God, the fingers of Gods hand, and ſacred actuaries and pen-men of his Counſells, might be ſent downe from heauen vnto vs, we wold bee glad to take the wideſt perambulation that is, to looke anie of them on the face: but in the reſurrecti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, we ſhall ſee all the glorious companie of the pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phets, the fellowſhip of the Apoſtles, the noble ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie of Martirs, and his holy Angels, yea Chriſt him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe face to face, wherefore we haue cauſe to wiſh &amp; welcome this our reſurrection.</p>
            <p n="5">5. I note alſo this aduantage in the reſurrection that the faithfull haue: it is their Bul-warke and wall of braſſe againſt all temptations, the Cittie of refuge amidſt their perſecutions in this world, the ſoule of the inward man, and bleſſed bee God which hath ſhewed vs this kindneſſe in a ſtrong Cittie. This was armour of proofe to <hi>Iob</hi> againſt all the fierie Dartes of the diuell throwne againſt his patience,<note place="margin">Iob, 19.25,</note> whereby hee was more then Conqueror, whilſt his heart like Mount Sion, which could not be remooued, was fix<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed and faſtened vpon the reſurrection.</p>
            <p>And this was as it were the latter gracious raine
<pb facs="tcp:18768:14"/>in the heate and drought of ſummer, which refreſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed the inheritance of God, euen the ſoules of his Saints, and as the ſweete wood throwne into the waters of <hi>Marah</hi> that tooke away the bitterneſſe of it, when in the daies of <hi>Antiochus</hi> they were vnder the Croſſe, and endured ſtrange torments: for they looked as the Spirit of God ſaith: <hi>for a better reſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rection.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Heb. 11.3<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Dauid</hi> by this Target that couered his heart could fight like a man, and breake euerie Speare that was lift vp againſt him, &amp; was in a readines for euerie enimie when he came in the gate, of which he doubted not to make this godly boaſt ſaying. <hi>Though I walke through the middest of the shaddow of death,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 23.4</note> 
               <hi>I will feare none euill: for thou art with me, thy rod &amp; thy staffe comfort me.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Phil. 1.21</note> This made <hi>Paule</hi> to ſay that it was life for him to die, becauſe it was lucre and gaine to him. And the ſame Apoſtle being the mouth of the reſt ſaith: <hi>Therfore we faint not,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Cor. 4.2</note> 
               <hi>becauſe we know though the outward man perish, the inward man shal be renued dayly, while we look not on the things that are ſeene, but on the thinges that are not ſeene.</hi> For that which the left hand of nature pulleth down, the right hand of the creator ſhall builde vp againe. The de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtruction of our earthly manſion is the conſtruction of our heauenly habitation, it is the ſame Apoſtles profeſsion:<note place="margin">2. Cor. 5</note> 
               <hi>VVe know that when the earthly houſe of this tahernacle be deſtroved: we shall haue a houſe not
<pb facs="tcp:18768:15"/>made with hands,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iudg. 5.23.</note> 
               <hi>but eternal in the heauens.</hi> For this cauſe curſe ye Atheiſts as the Angel did <hi>Meroz</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they goe not out with vs to fight in the Lords cauſe in the reſurrection.<note place="margin">Sa. 1.21</note> As <hi>Dauid</hi> pronounced a curſe on the mountaines of <hi>Gilboa</hi> that the clowdes might neuer drop vpo<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> thoſe clods, becauſe there the ſhieldes of the mightye were caſt downe: ſo a curſle of all curſſes and the full viall of the Lordes malidiction bee powred vppon the bodies and ſoules of all vnrepentant Atheiſtes, whoſe hearts are ſoe hooped and bound about with infidelitie, as they haue throwne downe this ſhield and buckler of all their expectation, which is the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurrection:</p>
            <p>But the bleſsing of the Lord be on the mountains of <hi>Armenia</hi> which gaue reſt vnto the Arke: and bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed bee all thoſe Chriſtian bodies and ſoules that reſt vpon this, and let this reſt with them, the Arke and the Cofer of his moſte gracious pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes. And oh that <hi>Dauids</hi> fooles that ſay there is no God, and ſo no reſurrection, who I feare are too rife in this Royall Cittie, had the markes of knowledge ſet vppon them, as the Leprous perſon had, whoſe garments were ſplit, whoſe head and lippes were couered, who was inioyned to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>claime, as he paſſed by, <hi>I am vncleane, I am vncleane:</hi> that all that ſee them might point at them, and ſay,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:15"/>
               <hi>There,</hi> there: <hi>Behold an Atheist, behold an Atheiſt,</hi> who are dead while they liue (by the ſentence of <hi>Socrates</hi>) becauſe all the cares of their life are but to liue: <hi>Non viuit cui nihil eſt in mente niſi vt viuat.</hi> He liueth not, that mindeth nothing but to liue, or as the Romaine Emperor ſaid: <hi>cui nihill in vita dulcius eſt vita:</hi> to whome nothing in this life is ſweeter the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> life: whoſe eſtate therein is no better then a ſtone, <hi>viuit et lapis</hi> ſaith S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Augustin:</hi> a ſtone it ſelfe liueth. But they are dead &amp; dead againe, as S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Iude</hi> ſaith: &amp; to be plucked vp by the rootes,<note place="margin">Mar. 11.13</note> as the Fig-tree blaſted by Chriſt his lippes: dead by natural vegetation, dead by ſpiritual execration. From the ſubiect of the reſurrection, we are led by the hand of the Text, to the tractat of the iudgement. And firſt to the circumſtance of the perſons in the iudgement to bee tryed, <hi>Al great and ſmall,</hi> without any difference of ſex, or ſorte. So ſaith <hi>Eſay</hi> in the perſon of God:<note place="margin">Iſai. 45.23.</note> 
               <hi>Euerie knee shall bowe vnto <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>,</hi> &amp;c S<hi rend="sup">t</hi>. <hi>Paule</hi> confirmeth it, ſaying: <hi>VVe shal all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 14.10.</note> not one ſhall eſcape: ſo he concludeth it in the ſame place, <hi>fiue or one</hi> of <hi>vs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> giue accounts of himſelf to</hi> God.<note place="margin">Ro. 14.12. Iohn. 5.</note> This propoſition is alwaies indefinitely deliue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red. <hi>All that are in the graues shal heare the voice of Chriſt, and come foorth to iudgement. All nations shal bee gathered before him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Mat. 13.15.</note> 
               <hi>Hee shall giue to euerie one according to his works.</hi> Wherefore the Lordes
<pb facs="tcp:18768:16"/>judgement is compared to a Barbers Raſer, which ſhall haue the haire of the head and the feete, euen the hyeſt and the loweſt, the Peſant and the Prince.<note place="margin">Iſai. 7.20. Iſai. 8.8.</note> It is compared to a violent rage of waters, which ſhall not onely fil the channells, and the vallies below, but ſhall couer the toppes of the prowdeſt moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines. Men lay their nettes for the ſmaller fiſh, but the Lord tra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>meleth for the great <hi>Leuiathan,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iob. 40.20.</note> and caſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth a line vnto his tongue, and peirceth his noſtrilles with a hooke,<note place="margin">Iſai. 27.1.</note> he hath Tewe for the great Dragon, &amp; the crocodile in the waters, as the prophet <hi>Eſay</hi> ſaith. There is no running behinde a tree with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dam,</hi> behinde a Tent with <hi>Sara,</hi> or couering our ſelues with a vaile with <hi>Thamar.</hi> There is no running into the hoales of Rockes, or into the Caues of the earth from the glorie of his Maieſtie. The Moun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taines cannot couer vs, the hilles ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not hide vs, from the anger of him that ſitteth vpon the Throne, and of the Lambe.<note place="margin">Iſai. 22. Pſalme. 62. Ioel. 2.9</note> Though we make our neſt in a Rock, yet ſhall we bee as a tottering wall, and as a broken hedge. Gods iudgement ſhall runne vpon the wall, climbe vp vpo the houſes, &amp; enter in at the windows like a Theefe. No ſecret or ſacred place ſhall then ſhrowde vs:<note place="margin">
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ephan, <hi>1</hi>
               </note> but <hi>Ieruſalem</hi> ſhall bee ſearched with lanterns: whereby make coniecture what ſhall bee become of <hi>Babilon.</hi> When the judgement of waters came vpon the firſt world, there was an Arke and
<pb facs="tcp:18768:16"/>a Barke to reſcue <hi>Noah</hi> and his famely. When the iudgement of fire, licked vp <hi>Sodom</hi> and <hi>Comorra</hi> like drie ſtubble, yet <hi>Lot</hi> was exempted, and the little Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie <hi>Zoar</hi> appointed him to runne vnto. But the vni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerſal iudgement ſpareth none, there is no couenant to be made with it.<note place="margin">Iſa. 30.33. Wiſd. 6.</note> 
               <hi>Tophet is prepared for the King</hi> and the mightie ſhall be mightely tormented. The Lord puts this text into his ſeruant <hi>Ieremies</hi> mouth: <hi>Say vnto the King</hi> &amp; <hi>the Queene. Humble your ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iere. 13.18</note> 
               <hi>ſit downe, for the Crowne of your glorie shall come downe.</hi> The greate mountaine before <hi>Zorobabell</hi> ſhall be made plaine: it is the prophecie and apho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſme of the Prophet. Corrupt Iudges ſhal then ſtand at the Barre before their judge, and be condemned, as <hi>Shebna</hi> was.<note place="margin">Iſai. 22.8.</note> The jdle, jdoll Biſhopes and Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters ſhall then be cut of in that day, as he once cut of three of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in a moneth.<note place="margin">Zach. 11.8.</note> Blaſphemers who now throwe out oathes as mad men throwe ſtones, ſhall be ſentenced to death,<note place="margin">Leui. 24.10</note> as that Sonne of the <hi>Egiptian</hi> was, that was ouerwhelmed with ſtones and died: Falſe witneſſes,<note place="margin">Zach. 11.5</note> vnder the burden of whom the earth now groaneth, ſhall then be ſerued with a witnes, &amp; ſhall reape the fruite, their wickednes haue plowed, as the accuſers of <hi>Daniel</hi> were handled.<note place="margin">Dan. 6.24</note> All theeues and eſpecially the <hi>Clerophagi</hi> of our time, that in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>groſſe the patrimonie of the Church, and ſay among themſelues: <hi>Come let vs take to our ſelues the houſe
<pb facs="tcp:18768:17"/>of God in poſseſsion,</hi> who haue alreadie broken downe the carued workes therof with axes, &amp; ham<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers ſhall be condemned in the iudgement with <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chan,</hi> who ſtole a wedge of golde and a <hi>Babilonish</hi> garment,<note place="margin">Joſue. 7.</note> and bee led to execution. All <hi>Polititians</hi> &amp; counterfeit Chriſtians, that look vnder the brow, and runne with the ſtreame and tide of the times, to engroſſe the proſperitie and plenteouſnes thereof, ſhall in the iudgement be ſtroken out of life,<note place="margin">Actes. 5.</note> as <hi>Ana<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nias,</hi> and <hi>Saphira</hi> were. Our Popiſh heretiques, and all maintainers of Hereticall Prauitie and Pur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>loyners and Barterers of Gods holy miſteries, rather then they ſhall want executioners, their own parents ſhal be glad of the office,<note place="margin">Zach. 13.3.</note> &amp; ſhal thruſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> through.</p>
            <p>Finally let all the ſort of Schiſmatiques that fight vnder the ſtandard of their grand Captaines <hi>Korah</hi> and his complices,<note place="margin">Numb. 16.</note> and would vnioynt gouernment, tremble at their judgement, the earth opening and ſwallowing vp <hi>Dathan,</hi> and couering the congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of <hi>Abiram.</hi> Of which ſaith ſaint <hi>Augustin: Quis dubitauerit hoc eſſe ſceleratius co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>miſſum quod eſt gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uius vindicatum?</hi> Who dooth doubt that this is hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nouſly committed, which is of the Lord ſo highlye puniſhed? When a Noble man in caſe of treaſon is brought to Weſtminſter Hal to be arraigned, the people in admiration thereof, runne in flocks and heapes thither: But what a ſight will there bee that
<pb facs="tcp:18768:17"/>judgement Hall, where the Lord wil hold his Aſſiſes, ſo many Princes &amp; Pote<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>tates, ſhal ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d without gard or retenue, naked, &amp; trembling, yearning, &amp; eating their tongues through griefe, &amp; ſhal receiue ſentence not onely capital, but eternall. If al the bodies that e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer were borne, might bee now ſeene in one heape, what a fearefull ſpectackle would it make? but there ſhall bee this obiect in the generall iudgement, to ſtrike vs all with amazement.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The next circumſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce is the maner of the trial, &amp; iudicial proceeding with the perſons co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>uented in the iudgment, &amp; that is, by the bookes &amp; euidences that are put in againſt the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: wherin what is ment by theſe bookes, &amp; how many bookes there are, it is to be co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered. By the bookes I vnderſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d the certaine &amp; in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fallible knowledge of God, his reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>brance &amp; care of al things, eſpecially of ſuch as co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>cerne his choſe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ones: ſo as their nu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ber &amp; names are before his eyes, as if he had <hi>amanuenſes,</hi> regiſters &amp; Scriueners to make en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rolme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. For as he numbreth the ſtars &amp; calleth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> al by their names: as he keepeth tale of the haires of our head, ſo as not one of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> fal away fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> vs with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out his foreknowledge: as his prouide<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce ſtretcheth it ſelf to the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dful of meale of the woma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of <hi>zarepthah,</hi> &amp; to the pitcher of oyle of the preachers widow: to the fal of a ſparrow fro<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the houſe top to the cloathing of the lilleis, &amp; graſſe of the field: to the prouiſsion of the young Rauens that call vpon him: ſo much more
<pb facs="tcp:18768:18"/>keepeth hee a Kalender of our dooings, and ſetteth our ſecret ſins in the ſight of his countenance. Thus Metaphoricallie in this ſence are Bookes giuen to God, the ſpirit heere alluding to the cuſtome of the wiſe, to Princes, Vniuerſities, Merchants, Maiſters of families and ſuch like. Princes vſe to haue a bill of the names of ſuch as appertaine vnto them, that they may knowe what number they haue, &amp; how to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uide for them in time. So the Lord hath his court in heauen, to which he hath not choſen al, but ſome be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore the foundations of the worlde were laide. Now the number and names of ſuch, he keepeth in as ſure and ſweet remembrance, as if hee had put them into writing Tables for the purpoſe. As God ſaid to <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes,</hi> I <hi>know thee by thy name:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 35.12</note> as Chriſt ſaith of himſelf to the Church.<note place="margin">Iohn 10.3.</note> 
               <hi>He calleth his owne sheepe by name,</hi> &amp; elſe where:<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20</note> willing them to reioyce, <hi>becauſe their names were written in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>.</hi> Vniuerſities doe the like: when they admitte any into their corporation, they cataloguize their names: Merchants and Houſhoul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ders ſerue their memories in matters of moment, by notes that they keepe of them. So this is the reaſon and cauſe of the Metaphor, and the ſignification of the Bookes, ſo often remembred in diuine lear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning. Gods minde therfore is his book: the Tables of our hearts are the writing Tables, aſwel as parchme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t ſkrolles, wherein are thinges engroſſed. The omni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb facs="tcp:18768:18"/>of God is the writing it ſelfe. Things are ſaid to be written in a booke, that is in the ſacred ſecrets of his breſt, as he knoweth them altogether.</p>
            <p>We finde three bookes giuen to God in the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures. 1. One is of his Prouidence, &amp; foreknowledge of all things before euer they were. 2. Another is of the iudgement. 3. The other is of life. The ſweete ſinger of <hi>Iſrael</hi> ſaith. <hi>Thine eyes did ſee my ſubſtance, yet being imperfect,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 139.16.</note> 
               <hi>and in thy booke were all my mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers written, which day by day were facioned, when as yet there was none of them.</hi> There is the firſt booke of his prouidence, &amp; foreknowledge. 2. The ſecond which is the book of iudgement hath two Tomes or volumes. 1. The firſt is his vnderſtanding of all our workes and wordes, according to which hee will a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ward Iudgement in the day of iudgement: ſo as this is inſteed of a rolle in Gods hand, wherein the names of all delinquents are ſet downe, and the qualitie of their dooings. 2. The other Tome is the booke of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uerie ones conſcience, which ſhall performe teſtimo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie to things done and vndone, which may alſo bee entitled the booke of life, that is of this life: which di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uine operation in the conſcience accuſing or excu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing, <hi>ſcientia conſcientiam</hi> the knowledge, the conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence, hath the name of a booke, becauſe in that in a manner is read, whatſoeuer by the agent hath bene hid. 3. The third book is inſcribed the booke of life,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:19"/>that is of Gods predeſtination to eternal life: which is begun in this life by our ſtedfaſt faith in Chriſt, ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cording to the words of Chriſt, <hi>Hee that beleeueth in me hath eternal life,</hi> that is the inchoation &amp; firſt fruits therof, after death it muſt haue conſummation &amp; perfectio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. So the book of life is a regiſter or role in the Lords right ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of the names of ſuch as are pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ordinated to euerlaſting life, whom God will alwaies acknowledge to be his,<note place="margin">Iohn. 13.8. 2. Tim. 1.19</note> as our Sauiour ſaith: <hi>I knowe whom I haue choſen,</hi> as St. <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith: <hi>The Lord know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth who are his.</hi> This book is ofte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſpoke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of in the ſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, as by <hi>Moſes:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Exo. 32.32.</note> when he ſaith: <hi>Raſe me out of thy book which thou haſt written.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Pſal. 69.29</note> By <hi>Dauid, Let the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be put out of the book of life, &amp; not be writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> among the righ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teous.</hi> By <hi>Iſaiah he shal be called holy,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Iſai. 4.3.</note> 
               <hi>that shalbe writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten among the liuing in Ieruſalem.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ezech. 13.9</note> By <hi>Ezechiel, They shal not be written in the writings of the houſe of Iſra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>el.</hi> By <hi>Daniel:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Dan. 12.1.</note> 
               <hi>Euery one shal be deliuered, that shalbe found written in the book.</hi> The new Teſtament doth often intreate of it:<note place="margin">Luk. 10.20</note> Chriſt toucheth it ſaying: <hi>Reioyce becauſe your name is written in heauen,</hi> that is, in the book of life:<note place="margin">Phil. 4.3.</note> ſo doth <hi>Paule</hi> when he ſaith, <hi>I beleeue thee faithful yoake-fellow helpe thoſe women which la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>boured with me in the Goſpel, with Cleme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t alſo, &amp; with other my fellow labourers, whoſe names are in the book of life:</hi> ſo doth the ſpirit elſewhere in the Reuelatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. <hi>There shal enter in it no vncleane thing,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Reuela. 21.27</note> 
               <hi>neither what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer worketh abhominatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                     <desc>〈…〉</desc>
                  </gap>
               </hi>
            </p>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:19"/>
            <p> Now theſe bookes ſhal be opened, that is the Lord whoſe fiery eyes of his omniſcie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce peirceth al things, that holdeth the ball of the worlde in his hands, and keepeth a perfect reckoning of our doings, ſhal ſet e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uery ones ſeueral ſinne in his ſight. And this diuine power ſhal ſmite open the doores of our co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ſciences, which ſhal cal to reme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>bra<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce our forepaſſed miſdeeds &amp; conuict &amp; condemne them. For there is a booke that is writte<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> in our hearts, which is of the workes of the law, the Lord hauing imprinted in the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> the notio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>: as naturally enduing the verye heathens with iudgement to deuide good from euill, &amp; to diſcerne betweene thinges honeſt and dishoneſt, that no man might hold vp for his defence, the target of ignora<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce. This we ſhall ſoone perceiue by our curſory confe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rence of the ten co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>maundements, with their politick ſanctions. 1. Of the firſt which teacheth that there is a God whom we al ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d bound to worſhip, the Ora<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tor <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Cicero Legibus.</note> 
               <hi>Nulla gens tam ſera nulla tam barba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ra natio, in quibus non miſideat deorum opinio.</hi> There is no natio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> ſo wilde and barbarous, that is not perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded that there is a God. The <hi>Athenians</hi> did ſet vp an Alter, <hi>Ignoto Deo,</hi> the vnknowne God. <hi>Protagoras,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 17.</note> 
               <hi>Abderites</hi> that ſaid: <hi>VVhether there be Gods or no, I haue nothing to ſay,</hi> was by the <hi>Athenians</hi> baniſhed for it.</p>
            <p n="2">2. To the ſecond, which is an inhibition of Idola<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try the <hi>Perſians</hi> gaue conſent, who as <hi>Strabo</hi> writeth <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 span">
                  <desc>〈…〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18768:20"/>abhomination, burned and deſtroyed their Temples and their Images. <hi>Cornelius Tacitus</hi> ſtoryeth it of the auncient Germaines, that they held it verie vnbeſee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the heauenly Maieſtie, to mure him vp within priuat walles, &amp; according to humane ſhape to ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dow him. And <hi>Numa</hi> the ſeco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d King of the Romains (as <hi>Plutarch</hi> relateth) held it verie heynous, that any ſhould comprehend the inuiſible God, vnder the ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>militude of a viſible creature.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third precept againſt blaſphemie, and pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phane vſe of this great name, was as duely practiſed among them. <hi>Theophrastus</hi> noteth <hi>Pericles</hi> with his inckhorne for an abſurd fellow, as ſhewing to a frie<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d of his in his ſicknes, certaine charmes, which old <hi>Bel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dams</hi> had tyed about his neck, vnder which the name of God was inuocated and prophaned. <hi>Tullus Hoſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lius</hi> was ſtricken out of life, by a thunder bolte, and was depriued of ſolemnitie of funeralles, becauſe it was in his minde to haue called out <hi>Iupiter,</hi> and ſo to haue caſt abuſe vpon his name.</p>
            <p n="4">4. The fourth of the Sabaoth, was by them ſolem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly obſerued: which their Lawes in that behalfe pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uided, aboundantly doe teſtifie, but heerein wee are to giue them the blame, that they peſtred and cloyed the Religion of the Sabaoth with ſuch a crew of jdle and naſtie ceremonies.</p>
            <p>Now this common ſentence of theirs, then in eue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie
<pb facs="tcp:18768:20"/>ones mouth, <hi>That which thou wouldest not haue done to thee, doe not to another,</hi> is the ſomme &amp; <hi>Epito<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie</hi> of the cannons of the ſecond Table: but yet let vs in a word particularize vpon them.</p>
            <p n="5">5. How they eſteemed of Parents, and of the aged, and gray headed, that goe alſo in Diuinity, vnder the name of parents, bee their owne Authors judges. It is <hi>Menanders</hi> ſaying:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>,</l>
                  <l>The great Gods are to wiſemen their Parents.</l>
               </q> The ſame Poet alſo ſaith:
<q>
                  <l>
                     <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>.</l>
                  <l>I will that thou haue thy Parents in all honor.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>Valerius</hi> giueth vs a memorable example of a Daughter, who being charged vpon paine of death, not to bring any ſuccour to her <hi>Mother,</hi> being ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>iudged to die by famiſhment in priſon, hauing ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſe to her, releeued her nothwithſtanding with the milke of her breſtes, which was ſo admired as it ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected the womans pardon. But how could this haue bene ſaith <hi>Valerius,</hi> had not the verie inſtinct of na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, weitten this law of loue within her heart? hence it is that <hi>Solon,</hi> thought it ſuperfluous to giue a de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cree againſt Parricides, as not imagining that any could ſo put off nature, as to bereaue them of their life, of whome they had their life. And how they ro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>garded
<pb facs="tcp:18768:21"/>thoſe that were in yeares, Parents for their age, this cuſtome of theirs ſheweth
<q>
                  <l>Credebant hoc grande nefas, et morte piandum:</l>
                  <l>Si Iuuenis vetulo non aſſurrexerit.</l>
               </q>
            </p>
            <p>They did account it a prodigious impiety and capital, for the young men not to riſe vp, and to doe reuerence to the aged.</p>
            <p n="6">6. Murther was of that execrable nature vnto them, as <hi>Romulus</hi> confoundeth theſe two words to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, <hi>homicidium</hi> and <hi>parricidium:</hi> adiudging ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>micide &amp; Paricide al one: yea the puniſhment ther<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of was ſo exquiſite, as there was not a man ſlaine by priuate ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d within the walles of <hi>Rome,</hi> for the ſpace of ſixe hundred and twentie yeares after that Citye was founded, as <hi>Dion Halicarnaſſeus</hi> doth report.</p>
            <p n="7">7. How by nature the heathens abhorred whore<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dome, and were therin a law vnto themſelues, before the law of God was giuen: the examples of <hi>Pharao,</hi> &amp; <hi>Abimilech</hi> ſhewes, who aſſaulted <hi>Sara</hi> in ignorance that ſhe was anothers wife.</p>
            <p n="8">8. Theft, by the <hi>Athenian</hi> Law-giuer, <hi>Draco</hi> was puniſhed by death: &amp; by <hi>Solon</hi> by double da<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mage: and by the <hi>Romaines,</hi> according to the proportion of the fellony, yea Vſurie which is thefts Daughter, is conſorted by <hi>Cato</hi> the elder to murder.</p>
            <p n="9">9. They made ſuch prouiſion againſt falſe teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mony
<pb facs="tcp:18768:21"/>as it was enacted among the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, that none ſhold be a witnes in his own cauſe though the matter were neuer ſo meane as <hi>Cicero</hi> ſaith.<note place="margin">Cic. <hi>2.</hi> Oſi.</note> And their ſaw alſo excepted againſt ſuch, who were knowne to be ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies to that perſon, againſt whome they ſhould giue witnes, as the ſame Orator telleth vs, giuing vs this reaſon for it: <hi>Ementiuntur enim ſape in eos quos o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derunt:</hi> Men will eaſily lye againſt ſuch whome they hate: among the <hi>Indians</hi> euery lyar was verie ſharp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly cenſured.</p>
            <p n="10">10. The laſt was verie requiſite to curbe our af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fections: <hi>Sophocles</hi> calleth this affection of coueting that is an others, a furious commaunder. It was the anſwere of <hi>Leonides</hi> to <hi>Xerxes,</hi> egging him to defec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion, and promiſing him the <hi>Grecian</hi> monarchie, vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon that condition: If thou kneweſt what thinges were honeſt in this life, thou wouldeſt forbeare to couet that which is anothers: as for mee I had rather die then doe it.</p>
            <p>But heere the natural mans conſcience is as a book claſped, and ſhut vp, euery ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> being willingly igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant of that, which the Lord with an iron pen hath thus written in his heart, eyther not acknowledging his miſdoings with <hi>Giezi,</hi> who could ſay to his Mai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,<note place="margin">2. King. 5.</note> 
               <hi>Thy ſeruant was no where,</hi> or elſe pleading a good intention in defence of a bad actio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>,<note place="margin">1. Sam. 15.</note> as <hi>Saul</hi> did to <hi>Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muel</hi> that vnder colour of ſacrifice would protect <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>
               <pb facs="tcp:18768:22"/>diſobedience. If there bee but a buſh in the thicket of Paradice,<note place="margin">Gen. 3.</note> thither will <hi>Adam</hi> conuay himſelfe to ſhrowde his nakedneſſe: and if there bee any ſhift in the worlde though it bee neuer, ſo balde and miſerable, the Sonnes of <hi>Adam</hi> will be boulde with it. <hi>Dauid</hi> would neuer haue knowne the man that was <hi>Nathans</hi> declamation, and the principall of the Parable: if the Preacher had not pluckt him by the ſleeue, and roundlye made him the applycation of it, ſaying: <hi>Thou art the man.</hi> The accuſers of the woman taken in adultery, drewe a formall Bil of inditement againſt her,<note place="margin">2. Sam. 12. Iohn. 8.</note> and followed it to the full: But when Chriſt wylled them to lay their handes vppon their owne hartes, they put vp their papers and ſhrunke away ſuddenly.</p>
            <p>If an othe would haue gone for payment, <hi>Peter</hi> had a luſtie one at commaundent in the deniall of his Maiſter, to put of a daunger, <hi>I know not the man.</hi> So long as there were eleuen els, vpon whom Chriſtes prediction of a traytor to come out of the company of the twelue,<note place="margin">Math. 26.</note> might be caſt, <hi>Iudas</hi> would make a queſtion of it, though hee knew it to be que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtionles, <hi>Maiſter is it I?</hi> But in the iudgement <hi>Adam</hi> ſhal be put beſides his apron of figge leaues, <hi>Sara</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides her Tent, <hi>Thamer</hi> beſides her maske, and euerie mans conſcience ſhal ſay vnto him, as <hi>Achab</hi> to <hi>Elias: Haſt thou found me, O my enemy? Quando Deus
<pb facs="tcp:18768:22"/>iudex erit, alius teſtis quam conſcientia tua, non erit.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>iudicem iuſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>um, et conſcientiam tuam,</hi>
               <note place="margin">Auguſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> Pſalme. <hi>36</hi>
               </note> 
               <hi>noli<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>
                  <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mere niſi cauſam tuam. Si cauſam malam non habueris nullum accuſatorem pertimneſces: nullam falſum testem refelles, nullum veru<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> requires.</hi> Whe<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> God (ſaith <hi>Auguſtin</hi>) ſhal be thy iudge, there ſhal bee no other witnes then thy conſcience Betweene this iuſt judge &amp; thy conſcience doubt nothing but thy cauſe: if thy cauſe bee not bad thou ſhalt feare no promooter, thou ſhalt not challendge any falſe witnes, nor call for any that is true. Againe ſaith the ſame father: <hi>In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terrogat te non alium de te: interrogat te, non vt diſcat a te, ſed vt coufu<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>dat te.</hi> He asketh thee, not any other of thee: hee asketh thee, not to learne of thee, but to confound thee. <hi>Auguſtin</hi> giueth vs a coppie of the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ditement by the iudge, which ſhal be put to the con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience to reply vnto, formed in this wiſe: <hi>Suſcepi do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lores tuos vt tibi gloriam darem: ſuſcept mortem tuam vt in eternum viueres, conditus iacui in ſepulchro vt tu regnares in caelo. Cur quod pro te pertuli perdidiſti? Redde mihi vitam tuam, pro qua meam dedi. Tu deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pexiſti in <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>omine deum, in infitmo ſalutem, in via redi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tun, in Iudice venia<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, in crace vitani, in ſupplicijs me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dicinam.</hi> I vndertooke thy ſorrowes to bring thee to glorie, I ſuffered this death to giue thee eternal life: I lay buried in earth, that thou mighteſt raigne in heauen: why haſt thou loſt that which I haue
<pb facs="tcp:18768:23"/>bought? Giue mee this life, for which I gaue thee mine. Thou haſt deſpiſed in man, this God: in infir<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie, this ſtrength: in the way, thy returne: in the iudge, thy pardon: in the torments, thy medicines. To all this ſhall the conſcience, which is inſteed of a thouſand witneſſes giue teſtimony &amp; conſent, which ſhall be as <hi>Barnard</hi> ſaith: <hi>Teſtis, Iudex, Tortor, wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nes, Iudge, Executioner: Ipſa accuſat, Ipſa iudicat, ip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſa punit, Ipſa damnat.</hi> That inditeth, that iudgeth, that puniſheth, that damneth. The ſhield of igno<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance which we ſhal then hold vp, ſhal be turned in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to a ſpiders web. The conuiction of the conſcience is an argument vnreſiſtable. The truth wherof by ſencible experience is known to euery one, that hath but a dramme of ordinarie vnderſtanding. For how<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoeuer we may bleare the eyes of men, yet we cannot plucke out the eyes of our minde and knowledge. We may beguile a Iudge by ſubtiltie, and terrifie an informer by our inſolencie, but wee cannot eſcape the arraignment &amp; iudgement of conſcience, which maugre our hearts, ſhall ſift our miſdeedes to the courſeſt branne, bring them to the light, proclaime them on the houſe top, and ſhall ſet downe torments before vs, for time and times, and when there ſhal be no more time, and ſet nothing but terrors about vs, which the Poets vnderſtand, <hi>fuciarum taedis ardenti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bus,</hi> by the burning tapers of furious and helliſh
<pb facs="tcp:18768:23"/>hagges. To conclude, our ſelues being iudges, wee cannot be acquainted. And there cannot be a grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter puniſhment in humane inuention, then thus to carry our accuſer in our boſome, and this is the <hi>Ope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning of the bookes,</hi> heere ſpoken of Gods omniſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence calling into our knowledge all our miſdeedes and our vnreſtie conſcience in the guiltines thereof, openly acknowledging them.</p>
            <p>We haue many dueties red vs in this lecture of the opening of the bookes. 1. As firſt of humiliation and repentance. This was that the Apoſtle would inferre out of the Sermon that hee made to the <hi>Athenians</hi> of the iudgement, the Text whereof was:<note place="margin">Act. 17.32</note> 
               <hi>The Lord hath appointed a day wherein he wil iudge the world in righteouſnes.</hi> For all our new Doctrine, wee keepe ſtill the old conuerſation. But for Gods ſake let vs thinke of the counte day, and preuent the iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t to come with newnes of life, as <hi>Iacob</hi> by rewards ſent before him, aſwadged the furie of his Brother <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſau.</hi> Let vs meete the Lord in the way,<note place="margin">Amos. 4.12. 1. Sam. 25.</note> it is the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell of the Prophet <hi>Amos:</hi> As <hi>Abigail</hi> met <hi>Dauid</hi> in the way to her great good. For by this ſhe ſtaied the ſword of his vengeance: and by this wee ſhall ſtay a more deuouring ſword, drawne long agoe out of the ſcabbard of his patience. To this end ſaith the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle: <hi>If we would iudge our ſelues,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. Cor. 11.31</note> 
               <hi>we should not be iudged.</hi> A former iudgement taken out of our ſelues,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:24"/>ſhalbe a Superſedeas to the ſecond judgement that muſt elſe come out againſt vs. To the due perfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ma<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ce wherof theſe foure things are required. 1. A due examinatio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> of our ſelues,<note place="margin">2. Kings. 5</note> becauſe the fleſh is as <hi>Gie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zie</hi> that lyeth to his Maiſter, that is to his ſoule, and will not acknowledge what it hath done. Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore as <hi>Elisha</hi> examined him: ſo muſt the ſoule exa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mine the bodie.<note place="margin">Iudg. 16.6.</note> And as <hi>Dalilah</hi> examined <hi>Sampſon</hi> in what part his ſtrength was, ſo is euerie one to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>amine himſelfe in what part his weakenes is. As <hi>Ie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hu</hi> did examine <hi>Iehonadab,</hi>
               <note place="margin">1. King. 10.15</note> whether his heart ſtood right toward him, ſo wee are to examine our ſelues whether our heart ſtand right towards God. <hi>Paul</hi> willeth vs <hi>to trye althings:</hi> wherefore it followeth by needful conſequence,<note place="margin">1. Theſ. 5.</note> that we ſhould trie our ſelues.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Iſaack</hi> tryed his Children before he bleſſed them. <hi>Salomon</hi> tried who was the right mother: The <hi>Ephra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mites</hi> were tried before they could paſſe <hi>Iorda<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>:</hi> Gra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiers try their Oxen, Merchans their golde, wiſemen their ſerua<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts. Therfore we are much more to try our ſelues. 2. Hauing found out our ſinnes in the next roome, we muſt confeſſe them vnto the Lord. In this duetie lyeth a great part of Gods glory, as <hi>Ioſua</hi> ſaith to <hi>Achan: My Son giue glory to God and confes what thou haſt done:</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ioſue 7 <hi>Cypian.</hi>
               </note> It is <hi>Ciprians</hi> graue ſaying, <hi>Somnium narrare vigilantis est, et vitia confiteri ſanitatis indi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cium eſt.</hi> To deliuer our dreame, it is a token of
<pb facs="tcp:18768:24"/>wakefulneſſe, and to acknowledge our miſdeedes, it is a ſigne of healthfulneſſe: which <hi>Seneca</hi> ſheweth by ſimilitude when he ſaith: <hi>Vulnera clauſa plus cru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciant.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Seneca.</note> Woundes that are ſtopped, are more paineful to vs: which hath iuſt application vnto the ſtoppage of our ſpiritual woundes. And how they will torme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t vs <hi>Gregory</hi> deliuereth: <hi>Si non confeſſus lates, incon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſus damnaberis.</hi> it vnco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>feſſed thou haſt hid,<note place="margin">Greg.</note> vncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſed thou ſhalt be damned. 3. Vppon this our con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſsion wee muſt proceede vnto a iudgement and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation of our ſelues, to ſtop the greater iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and conde<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>nation. Wherfore <hi>Auguſt.</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">Aug.</note> 
               <hi>Pec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>catum puniendum eſt aut ate, aut a deo: ſi punitur a te, tune punitur ſine te: ſi vero a te non puni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur, tecum punietur.</hi> Sinne muſt eyther bee pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by thee or by God, If it be puniſhed by thee, it ſhall bee puniſhed without thee. If it be not pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſhed by thee, it ſhal be puniſhed with thee. Wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore <hi>Bernard</hi> taketh bond by decree of himſelfe to performe this part of duetie.<note place="margin">Bernard in Canti. ſerm. <hi>24.</hi>
               </note> Hee ſaith hee wil pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſent himſelfe to his judge, <hi>Iudicatus</hi> non <hi>iudicandus,</hi> alreadye iudged, and not bee iudged. 4. Laſtlye to ſaue our ſelues from deſtruction, let vs call for the Pſalme of mercye for our neck-verſe, which is ſo infinite, as no affection of nature, or propor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of creature is able to expreſſe. The height of the heauen aboue the earth, the wideneſſe from the
<pb facs="tcp:18768:25"/>eaſt to the weſt, the tender loue of Parents to their Children, of Eagles to their young ones, are but light ſhaddowes and reſemblances thereof, they are not equall rules and meaſures of it. The mercie of God is the mother that conceiueth vs, the nurſe that feedeth vs, and that which ſhall keepe vs for euer and euer ſaith <hi>Caſsiodorus.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. It is alſo caution &amp; prouiſion againſt raſh iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, it is the vſe and applycation, the Apoſtle mak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth of it in two places:<note place="margin">1. Cor. 4.3.</note> as when he ſaith, <hi>Iudge no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing before the time, vntill the Lord come, who ligh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten things that are hid in darknes, and make the coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſels of the heart manifest.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Ro. 14.10.</note> Againe, <hi>VVhy doeſt thou iudge thy Brother, for we muſt all appeare before the iudgement ſeate of Chriſt.</hi> To God onely appertain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth the iudgement, and the iudiciall ſeate he keepeth onely to himſelfe, wherefore Chriſt ſaith: <hi>Iudgement is mine.</hi> Wherefore what a preſumption is this for the priſoner that muſt ſtand at the Barre to be iudg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, to take the roome on the bench that belongeth vnto the Iudge? the Lord wil be ſure to recompence this ſaucines with retaliation of iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t, as he inſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nuateth in this his cautio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, Iudge not &amp; ye ſhal not be iudged. But this is the common diſeaſe of our nature and as kinde vnto vs, as the skinne that we carrie a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout vs, we wil giue iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t of a mans inclination if wee but ſee his outward behauionr and action.
<pb facs="tcp:18768:25"/>As if he looketh downeward wee will note him for an Hypocrite: If vpward, wee conclude him to bee proud: If ſile<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t too ſeuere, if ſomewhat pleaſant &amp; tal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>katiue to be too remiſſe. If ſomewhat frugal too co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uetous, if ſomewhat liberal too careles, if ſomewhat coſtly in apparrel too laſciuious, if ſomewhat famili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ar a flatterer, if ſomewhat graue, <hi>ſtoical.</hi> There was a fellowe ſhot his fooles bolte at <hi>Pompey,</hi> and argued him of effeminate nature, for hee ſcratched his head forſooth with one of his fingers, &amp; that was the lux<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ate logique to conclude it. This <hi>Hydra</hi> doth more hurt then any one can diuine, yea euen in the church among vs: while he that is formall taketh the other ſide to be too peeuiſh, and thoſe that would reforme take vs to be too Popiſh. For my part I ſhal iudge of them in loue, and if they ſhall iudge of vs according to their luſts, I ſhall leaue them to their luſts: to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tend with them, wee haue no ſuch cuſtome nor the church of God: we will not take vp the Lordes pecu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liar Chayre, which hee hath in the hearts and the reynes of men. In many things we ſinne all, the Lord be mercifull vnto vs all.</p>
            <p n="3">3. It traineth vs to the timely reuerence and feare of the name of the Lord, and to giue him his glorie: the ſpirituall learning deducted from the iudgement which the Angell giueth vs. <hi>Feare God and giue glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry to him, for the houre of his iudgement is come.</hi> For
<pb facs="tcp:18768:26"/>be our ſinewes neuer ſo hooped about with iron, and our hearts harder then the neither moſt milſtone, the ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>mer of Gods iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t wil break &amp; mollifie them, or elſe there is no Iron inſtrument in the worlde can doe it. The <hi>Cananites</hi> were as contumacious a people as any vnder the Sunne: yet the comming of <hi>Moſes, Ioshua</hi> &amp; the people of <hi>Iſrael</hi> in military ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, ſo perplexed &amp; apalled the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, as their hearts mel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted in their bellies as waxe before the Sun. And ſhall not the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ming of the great <hi>Iehouah,</hi> riding vpon the heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s as vpon an horſe, &amp; flying with the wings of the winde, like a man of war, putting on the haber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geon, &amp; ſwoord of juſtice, which ſhal the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> be dronken with blood in heauen, more ſtrike vs out of heart, &amp; take our ſpirits from vs? <hi>Elias</hi> his comming to the Prieſtes of <hi>Baal,</hi> was their ſtupefaction &amp; deſtructi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on: wherefore Chriſt his comming in wrath and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, his face burning, and his lippes full of in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dignation, muſt needes haue a more terrible opera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in vs.<note place="margin">Pſalme. 18</note> If the earth trembleth and quaketh, and the mightie foundations of the hilles ſhake, &amp; be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mooued becauſe he is wrath: how ſhall hee not rend aſunder the foundations of our hearts, and make them to ſtacker like a drunken man, when hee ſhall come to execute the furiouſneſſe of his wrath?<note place="margin">Math. 2.</note> If <hi>Herod</hi> &amp; Ieruſalem were ſo trobled at the birth of Chriſt: what an intricate maze of miſeries &amp; troubles
<pb facs="tcp:18768:26"/>ſhall encircle the wicked in that great day, when he ſhall come to iudgement?<note place="margin">Exod. 17.</note> If the thunder clappes and fire flaſhes on Mount <hi>Sinai,</hi> when the Law was publiſhed, ſo quelled all the people, as they crouch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed vnto <hi>Moſes,</hi> and beſought him, that hee might ſpeake vnto them, and not God: when the whole world ſhall bee ſet on fire, <hi>Et incandeſcet eundo,</hi> and it ſhall flame as it goeth, and ſhall climbe vp to the midſt of heauen, and the higheſt ſhall ſound his ſhrill trumpet, to the dolefull and bloodie battell, what ſhall become of vs?<note place="margin">Heſt. 14.</note> If Queene <hi>Hester</hi> was throwne into a traunce, at the ſight of the Maieſtie of King <hi>Aſſuerus:</hi> at the ſight of the ineffable glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye of the King of glorye, how shall not all pal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitation and extremitye of paſsion poſſeſſe vs? If the ſight of one Angell put <hi>Daniel</hi> to an extaſie,<note place="margin">Dan. 9.</note> what effect ſhall the fight of ſo manye myriads of Angels haue with vs? which muſt accompanie the iudgement?<note place="margin">Math. 28.</note> The warders of the Sepulcher were dead men at Chriſtes reſurrection, wherefore deade and dead againe ſhall the wicked be in the ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerall iudgement.</p>
            <p>If the armed Soldiers ſent to attache Chriſt in the garden,<note place="margin">Iohn. 18.</note> were ſo throwne backward at theſe milde words of Chriſt, <hi>I am the man:</hi> when euerie word ſhal be a deadly wound to the wicked in the iudge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, how ſhall they be able to abide it? whoſe
<pb facs="tcp:18768:27"/>breſtes and ſides, ſhall then bee able to receiue the quiuer of his arrowes, which muſt licke vp all their blood and deuoure their fleſh.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine therefore of the opening of the bookes, openeth all our hearts: wherfore goe we not about to pluck out the eyes of al knowledge of God, with <hi>Dauids</hi> vaine man that ſaith: <hi>Tush God doth not ſee it, the God of Iaacob doth not regard it,</hi> who is there noted for a noddy for his labour: <hi>O thou foole, shal not he that made the eye ſee?</hi> The Lord is not liable to the ſcorne that was throwne vpon <hi>Baal, Cry low<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, for Baal may be otherwiſe imployed, or coaſting a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the Countrie, or happily hath betaken himſelfe to his pillow and is at reſt.</hi> His ſeauen eyes ſaith <hi>Zacha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> runne through the world: the circles thereof are broader then the Moone: And as he is <hi>Totus oculus,</hi> as <hi>Auguſtine</hi> ſaith: ſo he is <hi>totus manus,</hi> he is all hand to ſtrike: and let this ſerue for the Doctrine of this place.</p>
            <p>But there is an other wrighting booke beſides theſe, that is to be opened, bearing heere the Title of the <hi>booke of life,</hi> namely of our eternall life, begun in this life, and finiſhed by our death. But wee muſt likewiſe diſtinguiſh of this, as it is of two ſortes.</p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt is a wrighting in opinion and not in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deede, the iudgement of the faithfull which is led by charitie, being led blind-folde by the Hypocriſie of
<pb facs="tcp:18768:27"/>many, who make ſhewes of Godlynes, &amp; vſe ſtrange fallacies betweene the Temple and the Alter, to the enchauntment of their ſoules, as ſtaring vp with their eyes, eleuating their hands, ſmiting of their breſts, hanging downe their heads, wagging their lippes, ſighing, weeping, and looking demurely, with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny ſuch mockeries, which eaſily coozen credulous charitable Chriſtians. But howſoeuer theſe haue a name that they liue, the courteſie of Chriſtians ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the beſt conſtruction of their painted profeſsi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and wrighting them in the Church booke: they are not indeede in the wrightings of the houſe of <hi>Iſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rael,</hi> or in the legend of the liuing. For the Lord will ſtrippe them of theſe vaine ſhewes, and bewray their hollowe hearts and diſcouer all their knauerie.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond ſort, is vncreated preſcience, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternall foreknowledge, by which he acknowledgeth, and hath acknowledged thoſe whom he hath preor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinated to be his. Of this ſaith <hi>Auguſtine, Liber iſte apertus non admonet deum qui ſunt ſernandi, ſed pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>destinationem eorum ſignificat, quibus aeterna dabitur vita. Neque enim neſcit eos Deus, aut in hoc libro legit vt ſciat: ſed potius ipſa eius praeſcientia de illis quae fal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>li non potest, liber est vite in quo ſit ſcripti id est prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cognitj.</hi> This booke that is opened, doth not learne God who are to bee ſaued: but it ſignifieth the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtination of ſuch, to whome eternal life ſhall be gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uen.
<pb facs="tcp:18768:28"/>Neyther are they vnknowne to God, neyther readeth hee in this booke to knowe them: but rather his very foreknowledge it ſelfe of the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, which ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not be deceiued, is the booke of life, in which they are writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten, that is to ſay, foreknowne.</p>
            <p>Now heere we are to open the vaine of the liuely<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eſt and ſweeteſt queſtion in the Bible. <hi>VVhether hee whoſe name is once entred into the booke of life, may e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uer be blotted out,</hi> that is, whether an elect childe of God, ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> euer be a reprobate? Our anſwere is nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiue that he ca<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>not: &amp; the affirmatiue part is moſt de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teſtable, &amp; diueliſh. True faith doth not know what this meaneth, to houer between hope &amp; feare, as the Rauen ouer the Arke between heauen &amp; earth. Our faith layeth holde vpon the omnipotencie of God, as being in ſecurity of his wil, it being ours by promiſes before the beſt witneſſes in heaue<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> &amp; earth, vnder the wrighting of his ha<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>d, &amp; the ſeale of the blood of the Lambe: whatſoeuer hee would haue vs beleeue, hee hath liberallie promiſed of his owne accord, which hee would neuer haue done, had hee not minded to ſtand to his bargaine, and to be as good as his word.</p>
            <p>But let vs carrie away the cauſe from euerie gaine<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſayer by the power, and ſtrong hand of argument.</p>
            <p>Of the iuſt ſaith the <hi>Pſalmiſt.</hi>
               <note place="margin">
                  <hi>1. Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> ſalme. 1.</note> 
               <hi>His leafe shall not fade,</hi> as a tree planted by the right hand of God, and ingrafted into the ſtocke Chriſt Ieſus; he ſo ordering
<pb facs="tcp:18768:28"/>their goings, as they ſhall not turne aſide to vngodly counſailes, to the waies of the wicked, or take vp the ſeate &amp; chaire of the ſcorneful.</p>
            <p>The Prophet <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſpeaking of the kingdome of Chriſt, which is the church, ſaith:<note place="margin">2. <hi>Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> Iſai. 9.7.</note> 
               <hi>He shal ſit vpon his kingdome to order it, and to ſtablish it with iudgeme<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t and Iuſtice from hence foorth, euen for euer.</hi> But this juſtice is eſtabliſhed by faith in the regenerate, by which <hi>we stand.</hi> 1. Cor. 1. yea by which <hi>we liue, Aba.</hi> 2 If this be, out of crie true, of the whole church, it can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not but be verified of euery ſingular member therof.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Ieremie</hi> pleaſureth vs with as plaine a place as can be, ſaying: <hi>I wil put my feare in their hearts,</hi>
               <note place="margin">3. <hi>Argum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Ier. 32.40</note> 
               <hi>that they Shal not depart from me.</hi> This ſo ſatisfied <hi>Auguſtine,</hi> as he often to this purpoſe produceth it.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Hoſea</hi> ſingeth the ſelfe ſame ſong, taking his text from the Lordes owne mouth.<note place="margin">4. <hi>Argum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Hoſe. 2.19</note> 
               <hi>I wil marry thee vnto me for euer in righteouſnes.</hi> I <hi>wil marry thee vnto mee in faithfulnes.</hi> This Sermon is made to all the elect. And the reaſon ſta<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>deth thus: Chriſt knitteth the in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diſſoluble marriage knot with the Church, faith being the marriage ring that ioyneth the<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Therfore thoſe whome hee hath thus conioyned to himſelfe, who ſhall put a ſunder?</p>
            <p>The Lord by the mouth of the Prophet <hi>Amos</hi> ſaith:<note place="margin">5. <hi>Argum<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> Amos. 9.1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>I will plant thee vpon their land, and they shall bee no more pulled vp againe out of their land.</hi> The pla<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>ts are
<pb facs="tcp:18768:29"/>the elect: the plot wherein they are planted is the church, as ingrafted into Chriſt: they are planted therein by a true and liuely faith. Now to theſe is this promiſe made, they ſhall be no more pulled vp.</p>
            <p>The Church is founded vpon a Rocke,<note place="margin">6. <hi>Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>t</hi> Math. 7.</note> which all the driuings of tempeſts cannot ſtirre: that is the machinations of the deuil and all his darlings.</p>
            <p>Hell gates ſhall not preuaile againſt this Rocke.<note place="margin">7. <hi>Argume.</hi> Math. 16. 8. <hi>Argum.</hi> Iohn. 6.37.</note>
            </p>
            <p>It is Chriſts ſaying, <hi>All that the Father giueth mee shall come to me, and him that commeth to me, I cast not away. For this is the will of my Father that ſent mee, that of all which he hath giuen mee, I should lacke no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but should raiſe it vp againe at the last day.</hi> Here is the whole forme &amp; ſtructure of our ſaluation, and the compaſſe and dimenſions of it. For whereas the father hath giuen vs all to Chriſt, 1. Heere is our e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lection: So that we holde of Chriſt as in <hi>Capite,</hi> our mediator in whome wee were choſen before the ground-worke of the world was laide. And whereas thoſe that are thus giuen cannot bee kept from him, but muſt come vnto him: 2. There is our effectuall and liuely vocation, our comming to Chriſt being by the feete of our faith: nowe in that it is added, that ſuch as come vnto him, he wil not caſt away. 3. There is our juſtification, and the gift of perſeuerance in Chriſt. The concluſion, <hi>I will raiſe him vp againe at the last day.</hi> 4. Is the hand that pointeth at our glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fication.
<pb facs="tcp:18768:29"/>Vpon the former wordes of Chriſt,<note place="margin">9. <hi>Argume<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s</hi> Rom. 8.29.</note> the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtle <hi>Paul</hi> paraphraceth in this wiſe: <hi>Thoſe whome he knew before, he alſo predestinate, and whome he pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deſtinate, them alſo he called, and whome he called them alſo he justified: and whom he juſtified, them alſo he glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rified,</hi> which are the foure ringes and linckes of one chaine that are impartible, let down from heauen, to draw vs vp thither. 1. The firſt is our predeſtination to life in Chriſt. 2. The ſecond is our effectual calling to Chriſt. 3. The third is our Iuſtification by Chriſt. 4. The fourth is our glorification with Chriſt. The laſt cannot be broke<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> from the firſt, nor the firſt from the laſt, wherefore it is impoſsible the predeſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nate ſhould periſh. The reaſon heereof layeth in the nature of God, his will and counſel anſwering his na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, his nature being without variableneſſe or ſha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowe of change: as he telleth vs ſaying:<note place="margin">Mal. 3.6.</note> I <hi>am Iehouah and I change not,</hi> it is no way ſubiect to repentance, to which <hi>Balam</hi> perfourmeth teſtimonie:<note place="margin">Nu. 23.19</note> 
               <hi>God is not as man that hee should lye, neither as the Sonne of man that he should repent: hath hee ſaid and shall he not doe it? and hath he ſpoken, and shall he not accomplish it?</hi> It is <hi>Auguſtines</hi> apt inference, Shall man ſay <hi>That I haue written, I haue written?</hi> (which was <hi>Pilats</hi> ſpeech of the title and inſcription that was ſet vpon Chriſtes Croſſe) and ſhall God goe from his hand wrighting, or alter? Let God be true and euerie man elſe a lyar,
<pb facs="tcp:18768:30"/>that he may be iuſtified in his ſayings, &amp; cleere when he is iudged.</p>
            <p>It is Chriſts aſſeueration.<note place="margin">10. <hi>Argum.</hi> Iohn. 10.</note> 
               <hi>No man can tyke my sheepe from my hands.</hi> Heereupon it is concluded that the elect being deliuered by the father into the hands of his Sonne, and ioyned vnto him by a liuely faith, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not be ſnatched from him.</p>
            <p>It is Chriſt his gracious promiſe,<note place="margin">11. <hi>Argu.</hi> Iohn. 14.</note> 
               <hi>I wil aske my fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther &amp; he shal giue thee another comforter, &amp; he shal abide with you for euer,</hi> wherefore the holy Ghoſt dwelleth with them for euer, with whome hee hath once bene.</p>
            <p>If any thing could blotte or teare out our names out of the Booke of life,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>12.</hi> Argum.</note> it is ſinne. For that is onelye to be feared,<note place="margin">Exo. 32.33</note> becauſe God hath ſaid <hi>whoſo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>euer hath ſinned againſt me, I will put him out of my Booke.</hi> But this ſhall not ſcare vs, as being to be vn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derſtood of preapared, and preſumptuous ſinne, which goeth downe to the graue with vs, which a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal impenitencie doth acco<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pany. For as God could not be ſtopped by the foreſeene ſinnes of his Saints, from making entrie of their names into the Lambes booke of life, ſo when ſin hath done the extent of his ſpight, it ſhall neuer ſeperate his loue towards vs, wherin it thus pleaſed him at the firſt to enrole vs. We are worthie whoſe names ſhould be raced &amp; de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>faced: as hauing ſhewed our ſins as <hi>Sodom,</hi> caſt down
<pb facs="tcp:18768:30"/>our ſelues vpon the bedde of ſinne, as <hi>Iezabel</hi> vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon a bedde of fornication, drinking iniquitie as an Aſſe drinketh water, as <hi>Iob</hi> ſaith, and drawing iniqui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie with cordes of vanitie, and ſinne as it were with cart-ropes, as <hi>Iſaiah</hi> ſaith: &amp; the Lord puniſheth our iniquities by the rodde, and our ſinnes by ſcourges: but his mercie will hee neuer take from vs, it being tyed to vs by an euerlaſting couenant. Yea becauſe wee are written vnto life by God, wee ſhall not ſinne contumaciouſlie and ſtubbornely, or continue in it as the wicked doe. Our Faith may bee much perplexed with doubts, ouerſhaddowed with cloudes, ſhaken with te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>peſts, winnowed by Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>than, and the ſhield and breaſt plate thereof may be tryed to the vttermoſte by all the fierye dartes of the deuill: our faith may be challenged the field, and endure a fierce fight, and bee in an agonye, and blodye ſweate as Chriſt was in the garden: it may bee as the laſt ſparke of a fire readye to goe out, as the laſt gaſpe that a mans dying ſpirit gi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ueth: yet ſhall it kindle and recouer againe, and in all theſe thinges be conqueror.</p>
            <p>Bee the Sunne neuer ſo much vnder a cloude, it will breake out againe, and appeare vnto vs in his perfect beautie. Though fire bee couered vnder aſhes, it will execute his nature. Though the <hi>Philistimes</hi> take the Arke of the Lord, they ſhall
<pb facs="tcp:18768:31"/>reſtore it to the <hi>Iſralites</hi> againe. Theſe are aplycati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons to faith, which howſoeuer aſſaulted with temp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, and borne downe a while, ſhal riſe vp againe and haue the vpper hand of them, the Lord being faithfull and iuſt, &amp; not ſuffring vs to be tryed aboue that which wee are able to beare. There is an Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plexie of ſinne in man, which ſeemeth to ſtop his life altogether, but he ſhall recouer againe. Thus there was in <hi>Dauid</hi> an Apoplexie of adulterie, which he o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uercame: thus there was an Apoplexie of idolatrie in <hi>Salomon,</hi> which wee doubt not hee ſubdued: thus there was an apoplexie of crueltie in <hi>Paule,</hi> while he was a <hi>Saul,</hi> which the Lord did driue from him: thus there was an apoplexie of periurie in <hi>Peter,</hi> which his repentance ſhooke off. It is with a Chriſtian, as it was with <hi>Eutichus,</hi> that fell from the third lofte, and was taken vp dead, of whome <hi>Paule</hi> ſaid: <hi>Trouble not your ſelues, for his life is in him.</hi>
               <note place="margin">Act. 20.</note> Be not ouer trou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bled deere friendes in the Lord, the life of the inward man is in vs all, howſoeuer Sathan would ſtifle and ſtrangle it.</p>
            <p>OUr election is in God,<note place="margin">
                  <hi>3.</hi> Argum.</note> and not in man, for electi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was before euer there was man. For wee were e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected as <hi>Paule</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">Epheſ. 1.4.</note> before the foundations of the world were laide, at what time there was nothing but God, wherefore our ſaluation is cock-ſure as be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing wholye in God. For what is the reaſon that the
<pb facs="tcp:18768:31"/>heauens keepe their certaine motions? the Sunne, Moone, Starres, their certaine courſes? the day and night their ſucceſsiue returnes? It is becauſe the rule and gouernment of them is abſolutely in God, and not in any other creature, whether Angel or man.</p>
            <p>All thinges in God are ſtable and vnchangeable:<note place="margin">14. <hi>Argum.</hi>
               </note> wherfore his decree of our election is vnmooueable.</p>
            <p>Gods election is eternall:<note place="margin">15. <hi>Argu.</hi>
               </note> that which is eternall is inuariable, as admitting no beginning, ending or changeing.</p>
            <p>He that changeth his purpoſe,<note place="margin">16, <hi>Argum.</hi>
               </note> doth it in the ſight hee hath of a better way, or elſe becauſe hee cannot compaſſe it. Hence it is, that being not able to doe as we would, we doe as we can. But be it farre from vs to thinke any of theſe in God. For as his wiſedome is vncreated, nothing can be better then that he hath purpoſed: &amp; as his power is illimmited, and abſolute<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly omnipotent, it cannot as the armes of <hi>Sampſon</hi> be manacled.</p>
            <p>The reaſons producted againſt this infallible diui<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nitie, are ſimple God wot, and wil hold no tacke with vs, wee will ſingle out the beſt, and ſcatter them like foame.</p>
            <p>They oppoſe this Text out of the Reuelation,<note place="margin">1. Obiection Reuel. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>
               </note> 
               <hi>Hold that which thou bast, that no man take away thy crowne,</hi> that is to ſay, <hi>they of beauenly glory,</hi> to which the Apoſtles ſentence hath reference.<note place="margin">1. Cor. 10</note> 
               <hi>Let him that
<pb facs="tcp:18768:32"/>thinketh be standeth, take heede leaſt be fall.</hi> Wee an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwere that the Crowne there ſpoken of, is the Crowne of the miniſtrie, the ſpirit there directing admonitio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g> to the Biſhop of <hi>Philadelphia</hi> to perſeue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance in his function: leaſt being remiſle and de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectiue therein, hee be depoſed, and another con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſecrated. But let it carrie the conſtruction, they giue it: they ſhall gaine nothing by it. For the looſing of the Crowne of glorie is of double meaning.</p>
            <p n="1">1. In reſpect of our ſelues. 2. In reſpect of God. In the firſt reſpect which is of our ſelues, there is no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing more certaine then that wee may looſe it be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſo ſinfull as wee are, and death and not glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rye being the ſtipend of iniquitye. But ſecond, in reſpect of God that hath choſen vs: of Chriſt in whom we are choſen, this crown can neuer be taken from our heades, being ſet on by him that can neuer repent himſelfe of any thing that he dooth.</p>
            <p>Whereas they obiect to vs the churches of the <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pheſians, Theſſalonians,</hi>
               <note place="margin">2. Obiect. Epheſ. 1.4. 1. Theſ. 14 1. Pet 1.1.</note> and ſcattered Iewes, who were called <hi>Elect</hi> by the Apoſtles, and yet ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nie of them afterward were relapſed: wee anſwere that there are two ſortes of judgements.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a judgement of certainty, 2. There is a judgement of charitie. 1. That which is of cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taintye is in God onely: it is in men but in part, ſo farre foorth as they haue certificat from God of
<pb facs="tcp:18768:32"/>any mans eſtate. 2. But that which is of charitye is belonging to vs all: it being our parte to leaue the Lordes ſacred ſecrets to himſelfe, and to iudge the beſt of euerie one, that giueth his name to Chriſt, maketh a good profeſsion, and ſheweth the fruites thereof in outward conuerſation, God hauing reuealed to vs nothing to the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>trary. 2. Alſo the elect are ſo called of the chiefe part, as an heape of corne is called corne though it ſtandeth moſte vp<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pon chaffe.</p>
            <p>But they thinke they hold vp <hi>Alax</hi> his ſhield vnto vs, when they tell vs of that which <hi>Moſes</hi> ſaith,<note place="margin">3. Obiection Exod. 32.</note> 
               <hi>Blot me out of the Booke of life.</hi> 1. I wil not anſwere them that that is ment of the Booke of the Lawe which hee had penned, as ſome men doe: becauſe it is a baſe expoſition, and vnworthye a man of ſuch a ſpirit, as if hee had throwne out theſe wordes in his haſtineſſe, and heate of his blood. 2. Neyther will I vnderſtand them of the Booke of this preſent life, as if hee choſe rather to bee ſtrangled then to liue in his bones, albeit manye Captaines are content to dye for the common good, and there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore ſome would charge vs with this ſence. But be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it ſeemeth as golde that is too light, we wil not receiue it. 3 Neyther ſhall I giue them reference to the book of the couenant, to the Catalogue of com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Saints, &amp; of the church: as if <hi>Moſes</hi> would
<pb facs="tcp:18768:33"/>be out of the Rubrick in the Kalender of the church: becauſe we take it, that <hi>Moſes</hi> had a further proſpect and a higher reach then this.</p>
            <p n="4">4. Wherefore wee will willingly receiue the mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning they doe like of, that is: of depriuation of eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nall life, as if hee ſhould haue ſaid, put mee out of thy predeſtination booke, implying this condition, <hi>if it be poſsible.</hi> But he knewe it to be impoſsible. If anie ſhall thinke it an abſurditye in him to come in with an impoſsible conditio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>, I choake them with the like of our Sauiour Chriſt, who not being ignorant that he could not poſsible auoide the deadly cuppe of the red wine of Gods wrath, that was giuen him to drinke, yet put vp this forme of petition to his fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>Father if it bee poſsible let this Cup paſſe from me.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The like prayer hath <hi>Dauid</hi> againſt his enemies,<note place="margin">4. Obiect. Pſal. 69.29.</note> 
               <hi>Let them be blotted out of the book of life,</hi> wee reply thus to that, that their names were neuer in the booke of life, but in the charitable opinion of men, whom their hypocriſie beguiled.</p>
            <p>This Doctrine is much vſeful, but the chiefeſt grace it hath, is the co<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>fort it giueth vs in the greateſt te<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>pta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>s that beſiedge vs: while we haue in liuely &amp; loue<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lye remembrance, the loue of God towards vs, wher<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>by wee are grauen with an iron penne, in leade or ſtone for euer, in the Booke of Gods minde, and
<pb facs="tcp:18768:33"/>ſo can neuer bee expugned or forſaken. <hi>VVhy then should wee bee afraide in the daies of euill, when the iniquities compaſse vs to the beeles?</hi> It is <hi>Dauids</hi> ſweete aphoriſme with the double ſpirit of <hi>Elias</hi> to haue a plauſe, and aclamation giuen vnto it. I know nothing more deteſtable to God, and dange<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous to our ſelues, then to diſpaire of Gods mercie: which is to turne his truth into a lye, and ſet Sathans ſuggeſtions before his gracious promiſes. Wherfore we are of <hi>Hieroms</hi> minde, that <hi>Iudas</hi> his treaſon was not ſo great as <hi>Iudas</hi> his deſperation. The reaſon whereof is giuen by <hi>Iſidore,</hi> becauſe his tranſgreſsion was but the death of the ſoule: but his deſperation the introduction into the verie hell of damnation. Wherfore put but off the helmet of this hope, which couereth the braine panne, and the Target of faith, which hideth the heart, and we periſh vnqueſtiona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly. Wherfore be we not worſer then Lyons to riſe vp againſt our ſelues, but behold the Lambe of God, whoſe blood let it bee ſprinckled on the dore poſtes of your hearts. One deep ſwalloweth vp another: the depth of his mercies, the depth of our ſinnes. Deſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peration is a diſeaſe incurable. For the Phiſcitian would put to his helping hand, and recouer vs: and wee with our nailes vndoe all againe. <hi>Nil miſerius miſero non miſerante ſeip ſum.</hi> Nothing is more miſerable then a miſerable man, that commiſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth
<pb facs="tcp:18768:34"/>not himſelfe. Though it was the ſaying of an heathen, a Chriſtian well may vſe it. <hi>Qui nihil poteſt ſperare, deſperit nihil.</hi> He that can hope for nothing let him diſpaire of nothing. Chriſt hath ſowed in teares, that wee might reape in ioy: He hath troden the wine-preſſe of Gods wrath, that wee might drink the wine of his loue, &amp; be drunken with it. He hath borne the heate and burden of the day, that the wages might be ours: He hath giuen vs a cup of ſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>uation, that we drincking it down, might driue away all dread and deſperation: wherefore we hold vp our heads &amp; ſtand faſt againſt all the aſſaults of our ene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mies in this life, after which we ſhal enioy the place to which we haue of old by the Father been written and prepared, and which by Chriſt of late hath bene purchaſed, &amp; to which by the ſpirit vnto the day of redemption we are ſealed. Now to theſe three per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, one eternall and euerliuing God, bee all honor, praiſe, power, thankeſ-giuing, aſcribed in the congreation of Chriſt Ieſu, now and for euer. Amen.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:18768:34"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
